Well, it's 6:00 and I'll call this uh
June 1st, 2026
uh city of Cheyenne Planning Commission
meeting to order.
Will staff please call roll.
Mia.
>> Yeah, Bob, you're muted.
>> We can come back. I come back to my mic.
>> I heard his voice. Yeah.
>> Earlier.
Uh Justin Trip,
Tony Leard here,
Daryl Hibbons,
Megan Connor
>> present.
>> Amy Hernandez
>> present via Zoom.
>> Boyd Wickham
>> present. And once again, Bob, we'll try
if you can get yourself unmuted. I know
you're there. I can see you.
He's getting technical assistance.
I'll just when he gets back on I'll mark
him as present at the time when he gets
back on. But we do have a quorum with
those present
>> with those that have already asked
present. Okay. Um do we have any
modifications to the agenda?
Okay. Um, that I'll accept a motion on
the minutes for the May 4th, 2026
meeting.
>> I move to approve the minutes.
>> It's been moved. Do I have a second?
>> Second.
>> Okay.
Any modifications, changes, errors
requiring correction?
Hearing none. Will staff please call
roll. I guess do we need a roll call
vote for minutes? Okay. Okay. All those
in favor of approving the minutes as
drafted, please say I.
>> I.
>> Opposed? Nay.
Motion carries.
Um any disclosures, conflicts of
interest, exparte communications
that anybody wants to disclose?
>> Mr. chair.
Uh I I considered if I had a conflict of
interest on some items here and decided
that I do not believe I do. But uh in
the interest of transparency, I'm going
to tell you what the possible conflict
was. My son works for Microsoft. He
works uh at the data the original data
center in the long the North Range
Business Park has for about uh six or
seven years.
uh he does not have any role in the
planning of their future data centers
Cheyenne or elsewhere. He doesn't have
any role in the design of those data
centers and I don't believe whether
Microsoft develops any more data centers
in Cheyenne has anything to do with his
future prospects. So I don't believe
that constitutes a conflict for me.
>> Okay. Thank you. Any others?
>> Mr. Chair, I do have a relative in one
of the affected areas. It's been ruled
in the past that they are not a conflict
of interest, but I want to make sure
that that is still the case.
>> Okay.
Thank you. And as of tonight, uh, we
received two, uh, pieces of written
correspondence, one of whom is is, uh,
from,
uh, a woman, uh, in an affected area
whom I previously consulted with
regarding property, but it was not, uh,
the issue that is before the commission.
And with that, I do not believe I've got
a and and and she's not a continuing
client and therefore I do not believe I
have a a conflict either.
Um before we get started, um as those
present uh might observe, we've got a or
may or may not realize, we have a
particularly uh lengthy agenda.
And uh so with that um I'd like to kind
of give an idea how we're going to
handle the uh handle the items as they
arrive uh as they appear. Uh uh first uh
um
we'll have uh staff staff will uh read
an item into the record and and let us
all know what the question is that we're
trying to decide. you know whether it's
approval a recommendation uh just be
aware that everything on this on this uh
agenda uh we are mere merely a
recommending body making a
recommendation to the governing body who
has the final authority to say EA na or
otherwise
um
uh after that there'll be a presentation
by the applicant explaining the project
uh the staff will read uh and after the
applicant speaks we'll be able to ask
questions question of the applicant. The
staff will present uh uh the staff
report and field questions from the
commission uh with occasional follow-ups
from the applicant trying to get clarifi
clarification for the commission and
those present what's going on.
Um and then uh we will take public
comment. Um uh for those that have not
been here before, the way we conduct uh
public comment is uh uh we're hopeful
that the public can provide information
that's not otherwise available to us. Um
argument is is is acceptable. Uh even
questions are acceptable. Just be aware
that uh questions will not be answered
until uh after we have closed public
comment and and then staff and applicant
can uh respond and answer the questions
posed by the public. Um during the uh
public comment period, we're going to uh
limit uh speaking time to each member uh
from the public to three minutes,
please, so that we can get through this
agenda
uh and and give everybody a chance to
talk and and give due attention to each
of the items on the agenda. Um once
we've closed public comment and and and
received uh
answers to questions um the commission
can then if we've got some more
questions we want to uh address after
public comment is closed. We can ask
staff uh the applicant or maybe a member
of the public that brought uh
information to light that that needs
follow-up questions.
Then uh the comm uh commission will
have a have a motion deliberation and
vote. Um and with that
uh will staff please read item A into
the record.
do that for B and C.
Item A, PUDC-26-70
5631 Charles Street assigned zoning
>> and as the applicant will staff please
read the staff report
>> or I guess present the staff report.
Don't read it verbatim.
man all pulled up and everything. Um,
>> Mr. Chair, through through you that is
there not a separate applicant? I don't
think the city's the end
>> uh for an assigned zoning. Uh, yes, the
city is.
>> And Mr. Chair, real quick.
>> Okay, I'm with you.
>> I will mention there are two more
assigned zonings on the agenda and I
accidentally did put an agent. Those
will not have agents on those assigned
zonings.
>> Are we ready? Okay,
>> we we are ready.
>> Mr. Chair, members of the commission,
Morgan Dennis Planning and Development.
This is an assigned zoning for an owner
petitioned annexation at 5631 Charles
Street. The current zoning is county
land use. This zone allows for a variety
of uses. The future land use map
designates this area as mixeduse
residential. The current use of the
property is residential.
Lots that are similar in size and
location have been zoned AR agricultural
residential. While the current use may
not involve agricultural activities, the
parcel is large enough to sustain
sustain limited agricultural uses and
should be zoned to accommodate these
potential uses. After meeting all review
criteria, staff recommends approval. And
I stand for questions.
Um just a quick question and maybe for
the edification of the audience. Um can
you please remind us what the the
purpose of an assigned zoning is and and
and why that's unique from a typical
zoning application.
>> Mr. Chair, counterway planning and
development department. So assigned
zonings are basically they go along with
annexations. Um with these we don't
discuss annexation. Annexation is not
discussed at planning commission.
Annexation is discussed at city council
only. So with this we are strictly
talking about the assigned zoning. The
assigned zoning is basically staff looks
at what is the current county zone, what
is the current use of the property,
what's the surrounding zoning, and staff
determines what the kind of closest city
zone we can give it when it's annexed.
Um, this is basically to give it a base
zone. Um, if a property owner wants to
request a different zone than the
assigned zoning, then that's when you'll
have a zoning map amendment that will
also follow on the agenda. In this case,
um they're perfectly fine with the
assigned zoning. It is just for
residents. Later on the agenda, you will
see uh there is an assigned zoning
followed by a couple of items um to
change the zone district from what staff
would assign it. Um again, the assigned
zoning is basically the base zone that
comes with the annexation. Uh but that
is the only thing being discussed with
any assigned zoning is the zone
district. is the zone that staff is
proposing for it to be assigned the
correct zone that it should be assigned
based on its current use, its current
zone district in the county and
surrounding uses and zoning.
>> Okay. Thank you. And to the best of your
knowledge, would the assigned zoning
render any current use non-conforming?
>> Mr. Chair, through you. Um, no, not that
staff is aware of.
Members of the commission, questions of
staff,
before I open this up for public
comment.
Okay, with that,
uh, I'll open public comment on this
item. Are there any members of the
public who wish to speak to this matter?
Going once. Going twice. Are there any
members of the public on Zoom seeking to
speak?
With that, public comment is closed.
I'll look for a motion.
Uh Mr. Chair, I move to recommend the
governing body approve the assigned
zoning for the north half of tracks
three and four to AR agricultural
residential, noting that the project
meets the review criteria for approval.
>> Second.
>> I second.
And Mr. Chair, I would like to note that
um Bob Mia is online and present.
>> Thank you, Connor. Okay. Uh any
discussion by the commission of this
item
hearing? None. Will staff please call
roll.
>> Megan Connor.
>> I.
>> Tony Lair.
>> Amy Hernandez. I
>> Mathia.
>> I Mr. Chair, that motion passes.
>> Okay. Thank you.
Um, next, I think we'd like to have uh
items both items B and C presented
concurrently. We'll vote on them
separately, but they appear to be
related to the same project.
So, staff, please read items B and C
into the record.
Item B, PUDC-26-
uh 1111 Cheyenne 98 future land use map
amendment. And item C, PUDC-26-76,
Cheyenne 98 zoning map amendment.
Is staff looking at the same agenda that
I am looking at?
I had 2611 and had 2676.
Okay.
Okay. Okay. Uh do we have an agent
present for these items?
Okay. Please state your name, address,
affiliation into the record.
>> Good evening. Uh my name is Matt Hingel.
I'm with Westside Property Investment
Company. Um the applicant uh address is
8350 East Crescent uh Avenue, Greenwood
Village, Colorado 8011.
>> What have you got for us?
So, um, I'm here tonight on I'm
representing Westside Property
Investment Company. We're a uh
Colorado-based real estate developer. We
have 40 real estate development projects
from PBLO up to uh Fort Collins. Uh,
this is our first um um time uh you
know, working to do business here in
Wyoming and in the in the city of
Cheyenne. We're we're really excited
about um the opportunities up in this
market um and and what we do. We we
position properties for um future
development. And what that means is
we'll um purchase the property, we'll
complete the entitlements for the
property, and then many times we'll put
in large infrastructure. That could be
off-site water and sewer lines, that
could be um you know, major roads to the
site and things like that. And that's
what we're proposing to do um here at
this site. This this 90 acre site is
just to the um southwest of the I80 and
I25 interchange. Um recently you um saw
the True Grit property come through um
the process for for basically the same
as what we're doing here, which is
amending the comp plan um to mixeduse
employment as well as reszoning the
property to um um light industrial and
and what the reason we want to do light
industrial is we'd really like to make
this a a highass uh business park that
can attract um manufacturing ing um
distribution, bottling plants, data
centers, kind of the whole list. Given
the given the proximity of the site to
to existing infrastructure, um we feel
it's a a very marketable site to provide
um industrial solutions for fortune 500
companies. Um so, you know, that's why
we're here tonight and we wanted to um
I'm here to answer any questions if you
have them.
Any
questions from commissioner?
>> Mr. Chair, I do have a question. Um, I
find this this came right after the the
True Grit and the Stanbury Farm moving
to light industrial. Is this coupled
with that? Do you intend to link these
two together?
>> It's not. That was purely by chance. Um,
we I I've talked to the I forget the
gentleman's name, the True Grit owner.
Um, but we are in in no way tied
together other than one conversation I
had with him over the phone about um
because I I I when I saw this come up, I
asked I asked him um you know what he
was planning and and the process and
such and and so we just had a cordial
conversation but but we are not tied
together.
>> Mr. share a follow-up question and and
perhaps it's just coincidence, but when
I look up the owner of this property,
their registered agent resides at the
True Grit Land Development address that
came in for a reasonzone last time. So,
um,
can you speak to that at all?
>> So, I So, the owner I'm working with
actually,
and I think the address is actually
Todd, he actually lives in South
Carolina. I think he's originally from
this area.
um Ken Clark, but but I
I I haven't ever I didn't know if that
was the case and and uh I I'll have to
ask around, but the gentleman I work
with is is out of South Carolina.
>> I've got a question for you. Um and
we've already got this zoned as a as a
business zone. Um, do you have any
insight into which particular l uh uses
that are available with a light
industrial zone that are not available
with the current zone that you
anticipate uh seeing in the future or at
least being entitled to use that can't
do now? I I think it's manufacturing
potential data centers. Um you know, we
want and and when we talk to industrial
users, um they want to know the site
they're coming to is only going to be
industrial, not potentially residential
on a future parcel. Um so part of it
just optics as far market for marketing
this to to end users, if that makes
sense.
>> Mr. chair a follow-up question to that.
Um, manufacturing just out of curiosity,
what do we still make in America?
>> Um, you know, so one of the things
that's actually I I believe that is
coming up this way from Colorado is the
Eagleclaw
um fishing company that that makes hooks
and lures and whatnot. So, there's
there's items like that. Um, there's
chip manufacturing um popping up in
certain portions of the country. Um, in
Denver, there was recently a factory
that makes Zins, um, Philip Morris
factory that popped up out by the
airport. Um, so there's there's a
there's a pretty steady flow of of of
manufacturing um that that we're seeing.
Um, and we think it's great because
they're great um, job producers.
>> Mr. Chair, followup question to that.
Um, do you find when you work on all
these projects that that you put your
industrial zones in established
residential neighborhoods?
>> Um, so I I I think the
the property to the east is very heavy
industrial. I mean, it's a tank farm.
>> Well, the property to the east is
secluded by the railroad tracks and a
hill. It is isolated from the property
in question
>> somewhat. I think the railroad itself is
is a fairly intense use. Um, and then to
the to the northeast there's a trucking
company. Um, certainly to the north now
that's been reszoned to light
industrial. Um, you know, while there's
residential, have we built industrial
next to residential? Absolutely. Um, we
we put in, you know, buffers from the
houses, we use down lighting so the
lighting is not bothering folks at
night. Um so so we do everything we can
to make sure um it's it's not a
nuisance.
Do you know if a mix of projected uses
uh would be objectionable to your target
market? Uh I note that we current our
current land use ma map map uh or future
land use map does contemplate both light
light industrial and mix mixed use
business here and I share my my
colleagues concern about
no buffer at all that that we usually
would plan for between residential urban
residential and industrial
and Is does our current
our current concept prevent you from
doing what you what you want to do? It
it does. It does. And I you know, like I
mentioned, I think having the
residential use on the parcel
um gives users pause. Um
and
um there there's certain uses that that
I think are subject to special review
under the existing zoning where where we
don't want to be subject to um special
review. Um and and
you know, as I mentioned, we we do
everything we can to help help buffer um
adjoining neighbors from from whatever
the use might be. Um,
you know, I, you know, honestly, some, I
think some of the existing, you know,
this property could have apartment after
apartment after apartment with a lot of
traffic, sewer, water, and implications
um that I think
really end up having a bigger impact on
the neighbors than than a generally,
you know, unobtrusive warehouse or
whatever it might be.
Mr. Chair, a followup to that if I may.
So, um,
you're not privy to our insights, but
we've reviewed this in the past as far
as infrastructure. Um, there's not a lot
out there. So, what is your plan? How
are you going to make this this a viable
area with the infrastructure you want to
put in and where do you plan on putting
that?
>> So, there's a sewer line in um Southwest
Drive to the west that's about 700 ft
away. um that that should provide a a
natural connection point given the the
grading on the site. Um water is is the
harder um solution. There is no um
municipal water um in this pocket on
this side of the the railroad tracks.
So, you know, working with our engineers
at at AVI, there's there's a couple
different solutions. There is there is
water at the um industrial to the east.
um we could tie in there at at two
points. We could tie in there with one
point and potentially go north
um to connect north of the highway. Um
but but certainly there's some there's
some infrastructure that that is going
to need to be built to service the site
and that's that's what we do
>> and the roads. Um, same. We'll have to
complete a traffic study based on the
ultimate end user and, you know, make
connection points where they make the
most sense. There's there's currently
three connection points from Southwest
Drive.
There's kind of a connection point to
the south uh down to College Drive, but
there are there is public right away
currently in those areas. Um and and
based on on the use and the traffic,
we'll have to determine what what the
best um connection points are.
>> Well, I I find that problematic because
we you're asking us to determine that
the use is light industrial and so I
guess I'm asking what the plan is and
and what that's going to look like be
with have to assume the infrastructure
that's in place today.
Well, and that'll all be part of our our
site plan process where where we're
doing our traffic engineering and our
and our, you know, public utility
engineering with with with city
engineers to help us determine what's
appropriate and needed for the
development.
>> Mr. Chair, through you.
>> Commissioner Lar,
>> I I'm curious.
You expect you would sell this to one uh
devel or it would be a single use
development or do you think it'll might
get subdivided in the future and have
several different things going on?
>> It could have several. I I it could go
either way. We we certainly
um like and need to have flexibility in
that. If if we got a single user, that
would be wonderful. Um but we uh we we
plan to have more than one.
>> So, Mr. chair if I could follow up on
that. Sure.
>> So then back with your infrastructure.
So would you I guess what's your
workflow look like? Do you upgrade the
roads let's say like Broken Arrow and
Allison on the boundaries of this parcel
and do you bring the utilities like
Water and Sewer to the boundaries and
then wait and see what the layout of the
development might need before you do
anything internally?
Um I I think we would
generally initially
work on a infrastructure plan
upfront
um over the coming you know months if if
if the reszone's successful um to
accommodate
you know a highest use scenario.
Um so that means sizing the water and
sewer lines to accommodate the highest
use scenario. Um planning the roads for
a highest use scenario. Now if
but maybe that's phased. um maybe phase
one we have to put in these improvements
for phase one that you know we've built
enough for that phase and then there's a
phase two where we need additional
improvements or additional road
connections or a larger sewer or water
line um to accommodate that phase. So I
think I think we'll we'll plan for the
you know highest amount of use
um design the infrastructure for that
but certainly that may be built in a
phase manner if we don't if whatever
comes first doesn't doesn't need all
that and the city doesn't think it's
necessary
>> followup question Mr. chairman. And so
when you plan like that, um how many
users in the end since
you're saying more than one?
>> Um that's yet to be determined. It
really is. You know, we could have,
you know, five 20 acre parcels. There
could be five users. We could have two
45 acre parcels. It's all really market
determined and and userbased. We see
different types of users. um on our
projects that that just have different
requirements. Um I'm not here with a
user in hand. Um why we're here is
because in order to get a user in hand,
we need to have the right zoning, have a
plan for all the infrastructure, know
certain costs associated with the with
the with the site itself. That's how we
end up attracting um end users uh to the
site. Any
other questions from the commission?
Any questions from the commissioners
online?
Hearing none. Thank you. Please stand
by. Will staff please present staff
report.
>> Mr. Chair, members of the planning
commission, my name is Seth Lloyd. I'm
with the city of Shy Planning and
Development Department. The proposal in
front of you proposes changing both the
future land use designation and the
zoning that we will do both by two
separate actions in front of this body.
But we'll start with future land use
map. Um the proposal is to take this
land from mixeduse residential as found
on the future land use map and change
that to mixeduse employment. That would
support a zone change from MUB which is
the current zoning of the parcel to LI
light industrial which is the proposed
zoning for the parcel. the current MUB
zoning um allows and the MUR designation
I would say in the future land use map
as well allows for a variety of
residential uses and some commercial
uses. The um in the MUB zone apartments
would be a use by right. So they could
build apartments, single family homes,
town homes, etc. The um I will address
now the future land use map uh portion
of this proposal first. Um
before the property to the north came
along, there was no industrial
designations um west of the BNSF
railroad. Um it was all mix of use mixes
of uses of residential and commercial.
Um however, recent development in the
area was more industrial in nature. A
lot of the land to the north especially
was already zoned LI. Um and we've had
some light industrial uses um go in
there. We've also had some PUDS in the
county or planned unit developments
which are kind of basically custom
zones. Um proposed storage units along
Southwest Drive. Um so a lot of the
actual development in the area has kind
of been more of an industrial in nature.
Um and uh the
site and area definitely has some uh
restrictions from a transportation
network scenario and from a utilities
scenario. Um, it's already been
mentioned that we are have challenges
with water and with road connections in
this area, especially as the north end
of Southwest Drive closes with the
railroad on a regular basis. Um,
however, neither of these applications
really affect the transportation network
and the original comprehensive plan. Um,
that railroad, the interstates, the
railroad crossings, the um lack of uh
services all existed at the time of the
comprehensive plan. Um so there are
various reasons to both approve or deny
the comprehensive plan amendment. Um the
uh uh trick to this one is that we've
had a previous comprehensive plan
amendment that came before this body
just two months ago I believe it was. Um
that amendment went to the governing
body um with a recommendation of um I
guess it was denial. It's kind of an
awkward thing between our bylaws and
state statute as far as that goes. Um,
so the council took that um, uh, I think
it was a 3-2 vote in in front of this
body and went ahead and approved that
future land use map amendment and then
also approved the zone change to LI. So
now um, at this time we have a little
bit of a change condition from the
previous one. Now we do have mixed use
employment across the railroad and we do
have um, a a governing body vote that
seemed to encourage the uh,
industrialization of this area as it
were. I would note in previous decades a
lot more land in this area was zoned li
in historical zoning and it looks like
there was an attempt to move it toward
residential with the most recent
comprehensive plan. Um but it seemed
like the governing body was willing to
push it back toward industrial. Um
therefore uh on balance staff recommends
approval of the future land use map
amendment. Um mostly it's it's kind of
it as was discussed two months ago. It's
there's good reasons both to approve and
deny, but in this case, um the fact that
we've had a future land use map
amendment approved previously and
recently um tipped the balance toward
recommending approval of that
application. Um now going to the zone
change. Um the zone change really hinges
on this future land use map amendment.
Um the surrounding area does include
light industrial zoning. Um it does
include some industrial uses, but it
also includes residential uses and
residential zoning. Um so it's kind of a
mixed bag. Should the future land use
map amendment be approved? Staff
recommends approval of the zone change.
Um, and should the future land use map
amendment be recommended for denial.
Staff would recommend that the go that
this body also recommend denial of the
zone change. Um, I would note that the
MUB zone and the LI zone are more than
just uses. Um, there's also design
standards. So, for example, the MUB zone
would would encourage a more robust
street network with smaller blocks.
there is no requirement for small blocks
in the LI zone. The MUB zone would
require design standards on buildings
whereas the LI zone does not. Um and
then of course there is the use
differences. Um I did have a question on
this project and I would also note that
the LI zone actually technically
requires more landscaping than MUB zone
for equivalent development. Um but on
balance an applicant might choose to try
for the LI zone over the MUB zone even
if they allow the same uses because the
LI zone will allows for um
uh less in the way of design standards.
The uses allowed by the LI zone
including includes such uses such as
data center warehousing um light
manufacturing. Um the applicant has not
revealed to us any specific end user
here. Um, obviously it sounds like they
don't have an end user in mind at this
time as well. So, we would analyze for
any of those potential uses.
Um, we have had multiple public comment
uh comments on this item. Um, I've
received at least three different emails
regarding this item. Um, requesting that
the zone change not pass. We've also had
um I've had multiple phone calls and
also multiple people come to the counter
at the planning development department
to discuss this item. Most of these
people are neighbors to the project
and um object to the LI zoning at this
at this property. I would note that the
property is currently zoned MUB, so
development is possible already. Could
be apartments, could be some commercial
development. Some of the people I talked
to were concerned about development
generally, but there was a lot that were
concerned about the LI zoning
specifically.
Um with that, I'm available for any
questions. As I said, this is will
require two motions by this body, but
they're very much intertwined and
related. So, I'm available for any
questions on either of the two items.
Thank you.
>> Thank you, Mr. Lloyd. And I think I'll
kick off the questions. Um,
in looking at the of course, we've got
uh two issues here. um in in looking at
the proposed future land use map
amendment um uh from
mixeduse residential to mixeduse
employment.
Um,
could you please refresh the commission
on on the capacity for potential
residential development even with a
mixeduse employment future land use
designation?
>> Mr. Chair, the mixeduse employment land
use designation um discourages
residential development but would say
that it's ancillary use to a potential
complex of development. Um, our MUE
zone, mixed use employment zone does
allow for some multif family type
development. Our BP zone or business
park zone does allow for some mixed use,
um, meaning commercial mixed with
residential development as well. Um, so
the mixeduse employment designation does
not completely prohibit residential, but
it would discourage it as a primary use
for the acreage in question.
Um, in your report you mentioned uh the
difference in buffering that would exist
between the current zoning
and
LI should should the future land use map
be amended to permit an LI's resoning.
Could you spell that out a little bit
more? Uh, just to give you an idea where
I'm going. Um, I've got two concerns
with this. Uh, one, uh, we have
we have made several historic changes
away from future residential use in the
south side, uh, toward business or
industrial to accommodate uh, data
centers within the sewerable boundary.
And and secondly, you know, previously
when we were in this area, we were not
talking about uh parcels that were
immediately adjacent to the residential
development to the immediate south, and
now we're talking about just being
across the road. So, I'd like to hear a
little bit about uh buffering of
residential and just kind of generally
where we're going with res residential
capacity were to amend the future land
use map.
>> Mr. Jar, I feel there's a couple of
different questions there, so I'll try
and answer both of them. Um the first is
buffering or setbacks. Um the MUB zone
allows for and actually encourages zero
foot setbacks from streets. Um whereas
the LI zone would require a 25 ft
setback from all streets. Um the LI zone
would have a greater landscape buffer
against adjacent zones. Um however, that
is generally within city limits and does
not apply across streets. So we wouldn't
have a required landscape buffer to the
county LU zone to the um west or south
of this property. The um second question
I believe was regarding uh changing land
from residential designations to um more
industrial designations. Um we've had a
project on the south south of here um
project Cosmo which is becoming meta
which changed I think it was
approximately two full sections of land
um from a mix of residential and
commercial to a mixed use employment or
industrial designation. Um, we've also
had a request to change land out um,
west of town, west of the Air Force base
um, very uh, on the very edge of the uh,
planning boundary from urban transition
residential to mixed use employment.
However, that application is currently
postponed until September. So, that one
has not followed through. And as far as
I'm aware, this one um, just to the
north of this property is the third one
we've had. Um however we do have um this
one the subject uh discussion and then
the one there's one later on the agenda
that would also change some areas from
residential to mixeduse employment.
>> I I hope that answers your question as
far as the scope of what we've done for
residential to industrial.
>> Okay. Thank you. Other members of the
commission.
>> Mr. Chair, follow-up question to that.
So, so as you say that, Seth, I think
are we just updating the master map to
accommodate whoever comes through?
Because it kind of looks to me like
we're putting the master map before the
zone change and the frequency of
updating it that it's supposed to be a
master plan for a designated period of
time. And that definitely raises the
question about spot zoning.
>> Mr. chair um through you. Um the current
master plan that we have is
unfortunately way overdue for an update.
We are going through the updating
process in the upcoming um year. We
actually have uh proposals in front of
us that we're reviewing to update that
comprehensive plan. Um, and so hopefully
we can get some better guidance than we
currently have just because of the this
this current plan is is way overdue for
an update for the whole community, not
just spot locations. Um, on the other
hand, um, staff would not support zone
changes um, without a comprehensive plan
amendment and people have the right to
apply for those. So, when people want to
do a zone change in an area that is not
appropriate for the zone change, you'll
notice, for example, on the staff report
today, um staff recommends denial of the
zone change if the future land use map
doesn't get approved to change the
future land use map. Um but the
comprehensive plan has the um gives
people the ability to request uh
amending the comprehensive plan. And so
when they request the amendment to
comprehensive plan, we run that like any
other application and review that on its
merits. Um obviously
um couple months ago when an application
came through for this area, um staff did
end up recommending denial of that
project, but since that time council
approved that application um which kind
of u changes the calculus when it comes
to this particular application in front
of us today.
One more question. When I when I look at
all the LI that's on here, everything
that's proposed,
Cheyenne will be boxed in completely um
by LI and data centers. So, I've heard
about nothing but housing for years
since I since I started on the planning
commission. It's been quite some years
now. Um how is that impacting housing?
there's there's no vacant land left in
the city.
>> Mr. Chair, through you. Um staff has
definitely had conversations about the
impact to housing and the concerns
there. Um uh we don't want all of our
land designated for housing to change to
industrial. Um that would be a bad
outcome. Um when it comes to the subject
property and uh admittedly the
properties to the north as well um
housing developers have uh smaller
margins than industrial developers and
getting the required infrastructure to
this area would be difficult probably
even for um lower level industrial
users. Um, so one of the challenges of
this property is it may be designated
for residential development, but can we
get a residential developer here who
could invest the money in infrastructure
to develop this according to residential
standards? Um, I I don't know the answer
to that question, but it is a question
for this area is is can we get that
infrastructure here to get residential
to this to this area? um other areas
that we consider um have a little bit
more robust access to infrastructure and
it might be more appropriate to keep
residential there in those uh
applications. Um it might also be
appropriate to keep this area
residential. Um but it's kind of as I've
said multiple times, it's kind of right
on that boundary. There's two sides that
are industrial, two sides that are
residential. Um so um it is it is a
question for this board and for the city
council as far as is this appropriate to
extend industrial to this area? Any
other questions from the commission?
Commission uh questions online.
Uh I I guess I have one one follow-up
question. Um we're looking at this as
the application is as the entire parcel.
Um, is there any option to change the
future land use map for
all but maybe the southern most part
portion of this parcel
so that we have some sort of a buffer
and then as we look at the zoning, we
would be looking at looking at a
reszoning for all but some sort of an
intervening
parcel that have to be a better better
use or a better buffering use uh between
light industrial and residential even if
the residential is outside the city
currently.
Mr. Chair, uh three to members of the
board. Um anything is possible when it
comes to the land use plan as long as
you're deviating downward in intensity.
Um so something like that could be
included. However, it would result in a
little bit challenging, more challenging
review of the zoning because you would
essentially be changing underlying
zoning. And with this being one or the
zoning request, with this being one
large lot, the undesirable scenario of a
split zone could occur. Um, we would
highly advise advise against uh trying
to make an on the-fly type of amendment
like that. But if that is something that
you would like us to note in our
presentation to the governing body, we
could do so and then the applicant could
take that under advisement and they
could see if they wish to modify their
development request. Um, however, I
would like to note that a lot of the
different types of buffers that would
traditionally be between an industrial
development and a residential
development, usually those are elements
such as commercial, so higher intensity
commercial uses that are um, heavily
retail um, or serviceoriented. Those
likely would not have a marketability in
that area because of limited traffic
numbers. Um other items would be
multifamily development um of higher
residential development would uh be
something that could be an appropriate
um type of buffer. Um open space uh this
is very wide open open space. It really
wouldn't create the visual buffer that
one would be looking at. Um so long
story short, yes you could. However, um
I would just warn that it could
complicate the related zoning and um we
could just make that note as it moves
forward to the governing body and the
applicant could take that under
adisement to see if that's something
they would like to proceed with with
changing their plans.
>> Okay. Thank you,
>> Mr. Chair. Conor,
>> uh one more question, Mr. Chair. Um when
I went through and tried to look at
this, it's quite difficult because the
city's not updated any maps to show that
the um area to the north is actually
reszoned. And so what we were trying to
do is an overlay of what I was trying to
do was an overlay of maps to see where
um light industrial gets this close to a
residential neighborhood at a at a
parcel this big at this size at the
possibilities that could go here. Um and
I can't find that anywhere else in the
city. And so that is very concerning to
me.
>> Mr. Chair, um through you to
Commissioner Connor, two things. If
you're looking at the assessor's map,
that is definitely out of date. They've
admitted that they don't keep any city
zoning up to date on the county
assessor's map. So that is a terribly
unreliable map when it comes to zoning.
Our official zoning map that we keep is
on the planning and development website.
We strive to keep that up to date. the
industrial to the north was just
modified, so it was still going through
our GIS uh changes. So again, the one on
our website is the one that's up to
date. Don't even try on the county
assessors map. It's that far out of
date. Self admitted by them as well. Um,
regarding examples, there's an example
immediately to the west of this with the
industrial area along Parsley. Granted,
there is the separation between a
Parsley Boulevard, a tooling road with
industrial residential area. We have the
HR ranch development on industrial road,
which is immediately to the uh is to the
east. Um out at Burlington Trail that's
further east than Collins Drive. There's
a neighborhood with an industrial area
next door. um a lot of the um areas to
the north of Interstate 80 on the area
that's um near fifth and demi near the
Romero Park area and that is all
industrial immediately to the north. So
there are a lot of examples of
industrial where it is adjacent to
residential including areas um south of
Persian uh near Pioneer Park Elementary
School. Those are areas where we have a
residential to industrial interface
right there. So there are probably I
mean there are more examples uh where it
does occur probably than where it
doesn't occur.
>> And Mr. Chair, Director Bloom, I
appreciate that. But one thing is those
are historical light industrial sites
that have uses gosh since I was a kid.
Um that didn't exist today. Today
there's there's new uses in in the light
industrial zone that just you couldn't
even have thought of in the 80s. So, um
the the concern now is um with with
these additional uses,
uh these additional things that are even
possible today, is that still a zone
that belongs in a residential
neighborhood?
>> Is that a a question you're seeking a
response to? Well, no, but it was more
of a it was more of a statement because
every example Director Bloom gave me is
historical example that's been there. I
don't even know if you guys can find how
long they've been there because they've
been there for so long. And so when I
look at um all the reszones we're asking
for and the reasons that applicants are
asking for, those didn't exist
historically. And so when we're looking
at these maps, that is something that
needs to be taken into consideration.
Okay.
>> Thank you. Any other questions from the
commission?
With that, I will open this up uh for
public comment. As a reminder, um we're
going to allow each person uh about
three minutes to speak. Um if you have
questions that you pose, u uh we'll hold
those questions to the end um so that uh
we can try to address
all the questions at once. Um, and then
if there's follow-up questions that we
may have, we can call somebody forward.
Um, I'd ask that each person speak what
once and uh, please try to keep your
comments to new information uh, as
opposed to repeating what has been said
before. Um, but please help help educate
us to help us uh better understand what
we're looking at and and issues we may
not have addressed so far. Thank you.
And please remember to start by stating
your name and address for the record.
Ma'am,
>> my name is Heather Madrid. I live at uh
Do I have to say my exact address? I
don't know if I feel really feel
comfortable. I live in Harmony Meadows.
Okay, thank you. That'll work.
>> Um, I do have some questions.
Um, one is how would a more like higher
like higher dense whatever residential
um plan be an appropriate buffer for
another residential neighborhood, which
is what was I can't remember who
suggested that, but that makes no sense.
Um,
I wonder if anybody has even attempted
to find someone to build um that area as
residential or if the intent has just
been to find more data centers. Um,
I think we should plan for that because
as as it's been abundantly unclear, I
think we need to plan for what this
community at this point feels is the
worst case scenario and that this is
going to be a data center. To me, this
is not a mixed bag at all. I think that
at some point we need to consider the
people who live here um and have lived
here for years over people and
developers who do not live here.
Um
uh the re recent reszoning of the
property to the north I believe was a
was true grit and that person he I
believe is right there explicitly stated
that his intent and he said this on the
record is not for a data center nor is
it for a man camp. So I think that
comment mattered a lot in the
determination of the reasonzoning of
that property. Um, I just am also
curious
why
having outdated plans and maps is a good
excuse to move forward full steam ahead.
Um,
to be frank, I would probably lose my
job if I was relying on such grossly
outdated information to make such huge
sweeping changes to the entire city. I
would also like to say thank you for
first of all disclosing any conflicts of
interest. I appreciate that very much
and also for asking very thoughtful
questions. It's refreshing
for that to be happening and I
appreciate it more than you could even
possibly imagine. So that's it.
>> Thank you. Next,
>> Mr. chair through you John Sers agent
for True Great as I've been pointed out
in the crowd already. Uh I just wanted
to clean up one or two questions that
was brought up initially. True Grate has
no connection, no title, no nothing.
This actual property is under Garrett
Properties. I believe their contact is
Mr. Kenny Clark. It is out of South
Carolina. We have no hands in this
whatsoever. Um I know that Mr. Engel has
talked to uh Mr. Ernst in one brief
conversation and that is it. We have no
ties, no working relationships
whatsoever. So, I just wanted to make
sure that was clear and on the record.
That's all I have.
>> Thank you,
ma'am.
>> Thank you. My name is Michelle Cobb. I
live at 1415 Southwest Drive.
I'm in terribly emotional right now
because this is my neighborhood and my
home and I just heard that we don't have
to put buffers between a data center and
my backard.
My property is about 45 ft from where
this property is supposed to be going
into. How am I supposed to ever sell my
property if they put that there? How am
I supposed to look every day out my
front door at that and hear it? I've
been told that you can hear a data
center for five miles.
That's not even a mile from my house. I
can't even imagine hearing that noise
every night.
I think that it's important for you to
understand that these homes that are
sitting right up against Broken Arrow
will be the most affected by this.
There's no buffers.
And our wells, we are all on wells and
septics. And if you're going to try to
drill into water and well, well, what's
that going to do to our wells and
septic?
There's a lot of questions. And I would
like to say about this 90 acres that was
sold or sold just recently, nobody in my
neighborhood would have had any
opportunity to speak to that whatsoever.
Why? Because we're not 140 feet away
from this pro proposed spot. If you look
at the map, it's very close to us. It's
it even if they were and he says he's
not going to put a data center there, it
would still affect my neighborhood.
Please, please think about the the
people that are living in this area. We
What is wrong with putting more housing
there?
We would rather have that than have a
nasty industrial center with a data
center. Please, I think with everything
that has been going on in Cheyenne right
now, it would be good for you to hear
what your constituents have to say about
this matter. Thank you.
>> Thank you, ma'am.
>> Hi, my name is Sheri Brisco and I own
16005 Southwest Drive and609 Southwest
Drive. I am strongly against the
resoning of these 90 acres because it
will greatly impact my quality of life
and the quiet environment that my
neighbors and myself have come to enjoy.
The development would be located almost
directly in my backyard. My fence line
to their fence line is literally maybe
30 ft.
Bringing the increase in traffic, noise,
lights, and congestion to an area that
has always been peaceful and
residential. I am concerned about the
loss of privacy, the effect of property
values, and the strain it can place on
local roads and services. Reszoning land
on this scale will permanently change
the character of our community and
negatively affect the people who already
live there. I believe the concerns of
nearby residents should be carefully
considered before making any decisions
on this. Thank you.
>> Thank you. Next, sir.
Good evening, planning commission
members and audience and uh city staff.
Uh my name is Glenn Connor. My residence
is at 1304 Broken Arrow Road. I'm
approximately 90 feet away from the
proposed zoning change.
I received a letter in the mail dated uh
May 13th, which is exhibit A right here.
This letter looks like something I did
in the third grade. There's no header.
There's no really any type of address or
company or anything on the first letter.
Well, I complained to the city about
that. So, I got this second letter dated
May 19th. Basically, it's another
letter. Looks like maybe sixth grade
level instead of third grade level. So,
I thought it was a scam at first. I had
to come down and talk to the city
planners about it. They said, "No, it's
a legitimate letter." Well,
to me it's not
okay.
In the letter there was absolutely no
map, only a legal description of u of
the property was never addressed uh
future use. Um it just basically said
for zone change.
Um under LI basically the uh zone change
can be such as manufacturing man camp
calls it RV it's it's either I guess or
a data center and at this time it's
unknown. We have no idea what they're
going to do. There's nothing platted or
anything.
Uh
this does not fit the city master plan
building light industrial next to
residential zone which is county and
zoned agriculture.
I don't know how the city planners can
say that's, you know, can is going to
jive. It's not going to.
One of the reasons I'm against this is
because the broken arrow road was denied
the uh continual third turning lane with
the um widening the road and everything.
Um basically the engineers could not
justify the studies and the traffic
level that the engineers uh had put out.
They could not explain the land uh cost
and their studies. Cost appeared to uh
uh inclined with uh imminent domain.
Basically, they were going to take
property from people to widen the roads.
This is exhibit C.
The city has not called me back. This is
our petition which was supposed to go
before the city. I talked with Mr.
Lloyd. We went down and talked with the
uh city clerk. Well, sir, we have to uh
get the uh city attorney to take a look
at it and improve it. Well, that's been
5 days. I don't know how long it takes.
Are you going to wait till the city
we're before the city council to do
this? So, this is exhibit C. Has not
been accepted by the city. But I want
you to know that all the residents that
border this zoning change
>> time
>> have signed this petition.
>> Thank you. That's time.
>> Oh, I'm sorry.
>> Thank you.
>> Thank you for everything.
>> Next.
>> Hi, my name is Dr. K. Sheen.
This is very emotional to me as well.
I own um the long uh platted residential
lots
across um Wooden Shoe and I represent
myself with that as well as the
residents whose homes are on Wooden Shoe
as well as all of South Crest Heights
both on the north side of College Drive
and the Alice,
um I have a letter that um I gave Mr.
Lloyd to give you. Um I'm going to read
it. The two issues
and I'm having vision problems, so I've
got to change glasses here. Um
the following two issues proposed for
change coming before the planning
commission this evening are the
following regarding the 90 acres
bordered by Broken Arrow Road on the
west and Wooden Shoe Drive on the south.
Both the west and the south sides are
longestablished
residential homes and residential
property.
The legal address of the zoning in
question is such and such that you have
um of the 90 acres. First, the proposed
change to the long range map. The long
range map was designed to give some
uniformity for Cheyenne, Laramie County
area to avoid pockets of zoning that are
inconsistent with those around them and
for smooth transitions from zone to zone
to avoid major zoning differences of
zoning in neighborhoods. The proposed
change to the long range map from MUB
light industrial to light industrial,
and there's nothing light about it, by
the way. would create an eyes is
eyesore, health hazard, environmental
hazard and devaluation
of our homes and property values and
enjoyment of our homes and property by
allowing manufacturing, data centers,
limited industrial, moderate industrial
and industrial uses and buildings,
outdoor storage, impoundment yards,
salvage yards, railroad yards and
maintenance buildings and other
inappropriate development right next to
and in front of our longest established
homes and property and neighborhood. The
area in question for reszoning has been
kept as prairie and undeveloped.
Allowing light industrial development is
not only inconsistent with the already
established residential area, but would
create an eyesore, threaten the health
and well-being of residents, ruin the
>> enjoyment.
Well, if you could please read my
letter, I would appreciate it. And I
just want to say that the the light
industrial on the east side is primarily
prairie.
>> Thank you. and has been kept that way
for years.
Fred Schlacter, longtime Larmy County
resident. I'd like to echo what the lady
said earlier about appreciate your
initial disclosure possible um conflict
of interest and your very very
thoughtful questions to the west side
representative over there. Um, my
address is 2008 Barex Road and I'm right
on the corner of uh West College and
Barex.
And
yep, two or three points more than
anything else. Um, and and a question.
Um, the points would be, you know, you
guys remember where you came from. um
you know uh
you're in positions of of power now.
You're in positions of decision making
and uh you know we're just little guys
with residences out there and and
changing this to light industrial is not
a good idea. Um, you know, how would you
like to wake up across the street and
see them building a manufacturing plant
or a data center or something like that?
I mean, I've heard everybody's heard
stories about the data centers and how
much noise they make and heat they
generate and everything else and and
I've heard possibly a total of 70 of
them coming to the Cheyenne area. And of
course that depends on the number of
buildings you count and all that. But um
it's going to take a humongous amount of
power. And um I've also heard that they
they now they initially they were
telling us that they recirculate the
water. Now they're saying that they
actually pump this water down into the
ground down to the aquifer. and all of
our housing in this area depends on that
aquifer because we're all on wells and
septic. So, um anyway, just you know,
it's a tough decision. I'd hate to be in
you guys' shoes, but uh maybe say a
little prayer before you make your vote
and think about the residents there. And
um you know, there's uh bringing in more
residents, it sure be better than
bringing in a manufacturing plant or
something. The question I had was uh has
anybody looked at the effect or possible
effect on property values because it's a
huge concern of mine. Um everybody like
their property values to go up. Um I
think that's maybe a possibility here
but I think it's more likely to go down.
So please take a look at that. Um, you
know, there may be class action lawsuits
down the road uh if people's values drop
by half or something. So, thanks. Have a
good night.
>> Thank you.
>> My My name is Naomi Young and I live at
1404 Broken Arrow Road and my husband
and I also own 1311 Broken Arrow Road.
We bought the property for at 1311 here
recently.
We have a neighbor that is not in well
health and we wanted to keep him there
in on the property. So, we bought the
property from him.
It helps us out with our farm animals
because we have goats and we have
chickens and we use the back part of his
of the property. We still call it his,
but it is ours.
We keep him there. We His payments on it
are $400 a month just because we want
him. He's been a good neighbor. All the
neighbors up and down the road here.
We're close. We do things for each
other.
Selling off our properties, which has
gone through all of our heads. We don't
want to do that. But the values have
gone down. And it is it is a fact. They
do go down. And I've done the research.
We have farm animals. Like I said, we
have goats. We have chickens. We have
turkeys.
We have the wild animals that are out
there. They come through our yards. All
of our yards. We love that. To have a
data center or any of those
manufacturing things there,
it takes away our whole lives. And we
are all emotional about this. We've been
trying to maintain and keep calm and
things like that, but this is destroying
our lively or our home life. This is a
place that we go for our silence, for
our peace, to get away from the hustle
and bustle of our jobs and things like
that. This is our home.
This is where our family comes out. My
granddaughter had an a class. She came
out and helped out with the pigs that we
had had for her ad class.
Our other neighbors have bees and if
you've got the manufacturing things like
that, a data center, all of that, the
bees that they have will go away. They
will die off. They they will not produce
the honey. And that has been proven,
too.
I want to thank you for allowing me to
talk.
>> Ma'am, one real quick question. You
mentioned you were on Broken Arrow Road.
Are you to to the west of this site or
are you on the portion of Broken Arrow
that's further to the south?
>> I am directly across from where that
property is. We are right smack in the
middle.
>> Okay. Thank you.
>> West. Oh, I'm sorry. I apologize.
Sir, my name's Matthew Young. I live at
1404 Broken Arrow Road. Been out there
for about 43 years now. And I was
wondering if you guys would give me
permission to give Mr. Connors my three
minutes.
>> Sir, I'd like to uh confine each person
to their three minutes to prioritize.
And I'd rather hear from you.
>> Okay. I don't talk in front of people
too often. So, but yeah, I've lived out
there for 43 years. It's a a really
tight-knit uh neighborhood. Everybody
looks out for each other. A lot of
people out there have, if you want to
call it, small farms, chickens, goats,
rabbits, whatever. Uh my biggest concern
is it becoming a data center. Uh can't
remember the gentleman's name that was
talking about the sewer up on Southwest
Drive. We live on Broken Arrow Road. We
can't even tie into it. It's too high up
for us. So that property that they want
to change, they can't tie into that
sewer.
>> Okay. Just
>> Thank you.
>> Uh what else? That's all I got. Thank
you. You did a good job. Thank you.
>> Um somebody else knew, please.
And and sir, you you had your three
minutes. I want to keep everybody to
three minutes, please.
>> Yeah. Um,
thank you everyone. Um, my name is John
Nelson. I live at uh 1415 Southwest
Drive and my property borders
the property they'd like to reszone. And
like everyone else, my biggest worry
would be
a data center.
I've been researching the data centers.
As close as we live to this data center,
you and I would not be able to stand in
my yard and have a conversation
without yelling at each other. They are
so loud.
What Michelle said about five miles,
you can hear them at five miles. It's
more of a hum. It's not loud. But where
we're at, it would totally destroy
being able to do anything in the yard
because they run 24 hours a day, 7 days
a week.
It would destroy our property values. I
mean people who they have put these
centers near residential housing
in Fairfax,
Virginia, those people their h their
property value didn't go down. They
can't sell their properties. They can't
get rid of their homes. The ones that
are bordering these data centers.
So basically they have no property
value.
That's I think my biggest concern.
Mostly the noise.
Um,
I would much rather see houses and have
neighbors
living across from me than this light
industrial because a data center,
manufacturing,
these sort of things
don't sound like light industrial to me.
Especially when I drive around Cheyenne
and I see these monstrous 50 60,000
square foot industrial buildings.
Um,
and the other thing I'd like to say,
yes,
they did get approval for a storage unit
on Southwest Drive. And that storage
unit, the entrance to it is exactly in
front of my driveway.
Okay.
There's no hassle.
There's five vehicles in there on the
weekends
a day.
There's no noise.
If that's the kind of light industrial
zoning you're talking about, I'm okay
with that.
Trucking business.
Thank you.
Anyone else? Ma'am. Oh,
that's fine. Over there. We've got a
microphone there, too.
>> Hello. My name is John. I don't live in
this area. I live in North Cheyenne,
close to the range and converse. But I
heard about this last Tuesday when I
came here at city council from someone
who lives in this neighborhood and I
talked to some of the people there
yesterday. Um and thing is
I just think you have to think about I
know these plannings are are hard but
you have to stick up for each other and
I can't imagine these people I mean
their lives would be ruined if data
center or something else is um is built
there that it's really loud and and
polluting and um who's to say that
you're not going to do this close to
where I live at some point. I mean it
just erodess confidence of in our
leadership and our local um
our local um
leadership I mean the people who run the
city I'm sorry English is my second
language
um and
there are other ways to go about
planning this um if if you want to make
this a more industrial area you should
make it a co case to all the people in
Cheyenne and do something. I'm not an
expert but maybe eminent domain would be
better and say okay we want to
industrialize all this area but then
these people have to be moved somewhere
where they can have similar quality of
life at no expense to them. I mean, it
just looks to me by looking at the map,
and I did look on the on the computer at
these mess like these people like you're
trying to squeeze them out, like make it
so inconvenient that they move on their
own and just a little a few of them are
going to be left and then it'll be
easier to get rid of them. It just looks
really bad. And everything happens in a
context and this is in the context that
there are more data centers being
approved and people are lo I I know I
talked to like several dozens people
about data centers the last three weeks
and people are losing confidence in our
leadership in the city. I mean we just
don't feel like like you're up front
with us. It's it's very hard to find any
information about in general what data
centers are coming and they're approved
and all that. And I just want to say
that I grew up in a communist country in
Romania. I came here 40 years ago. I I
risk my life to come to freedom and they
were telling us we had no word over
there where we live where you know they
told us where to live where to work and
this is the first time that I'm getting
involved with alien lab and I put
messages on the internet about this
meeting and about the data centers and
I'm going to keep doing this. It's the
first time in my life that I'm doing
this and I don't think I'm the only one.
I mean, people, you know, they're going
to lose confidence in in in what you
people are doing if you don't take into
account that these are real people and
you're ruining their lives if you change
this zoning. Thank you.
>> Thank you. Welcome. And thank you for
getting engaged in exercising your
freedom.
Any other questions or comments?
Yeah.
My name is Janna Tolman and I live in
Indian Hills, which is a little ways
away. But some of the concerns that I
have is just the quickness of wanting to
put all these
um different industries in here
um in Cheyenne so quickly. Uh right now
we're in a drought
and you read through I mean we we have
like right now 21 data centers with the
possibility of 70 coming in in. And I
was reading um an article from Sunc
Corporation out of Miami. They're uh
they deal with water
and they said um if you have an open
loop a data center that will put out
uh water for 1,000 people. In other
words, 1,000 residents will lose their
water. A closed loop
um is onethird of that. So it'd be about
330 people that would lose water.
Um, depending upon what kind of resident
I mean industry you're putting in here,
I think you need to take into
consideration
water usage and our electricity because
not only are you
uh trying to change the scope of many of
the people's
lives that they've thoroughly enjoyed. I
mean, we've enjoyed being in Wyoming,
but I have a concern, too. It's like
Wyoming, Cheyenne, is quickly changing.
And is it going to be unrecognizable?
Is it going to be a place that any
people who,
you know, are homesteaders,
you know, way back to 1890 will even
have a place?
And and I think that that's something
you need to really take in
consideration. For me, people are people
in our surroundings and our comfort zone
is most important. And it scares me. It
scares me as to what is going to happen
to the landscape of our town, our city.
>> Thank you. Anybody else from the public?
Going once, going twice. Anybody on
Zoom?
>> Just going to bring that up. And for
those online, if you do have any
comments, please use the raise hand
feature. We do have one.
Sorry, I got to figure out which mouse
I'm using.
Charles Miller, you should be able to
speak.
And Mr. Miller, we have you on a
threeminut timer as well.
>> Can you hear me?
>> Yes.
>> Okay. Thank you. Um, Mr. Chair,
commissioners, for the record.
Um,
>> name and address, please.
>> This is Charles Miller, Laramie County.
Um, I appreciate the disclosure of any
conflicts of interest and I appreciate
the thoughtful questions that have been
asked tonight. Um,
now
I I am I'm
I'm asking you not to make such huge
sweeping changes to the entire city
without a complete and reliable record.
This proposal would permanently change
land that is still tied to residential
and mixed use planning into intensive
industrial use. And the neighbors who
spoke tonight made clear what that means
in real life. noise, lighting, traffic,
loss of privacy, and pressure on wells,
septic systems, and property values.
This is not a small zoning adjustment.
It is a major decision about whether
established neighborhoods are going to
be protected or sacrificed for a future
use that is still uncertain. The people
closest to this site are the ones who
bear the burden, and their concerns have
been specific, consistent, and serious.
We have also heard real notice and
transparency concerns when residents say
the notification was confusing or
inadequate and when the future use is
still not clearly defined. That is a
sign the record is not ready for
approval. If the city wants public
trust, it should not rush through a
decision of this magnitude.
So my request is simple. Continue this
item or deny it. Do not approve a
sweeping change until the planning
notice, buffering, utility, and
neighborhood impacts are fully
addressed. Thank you.
Thank you. Anyone else on Zoom?
Okay. Staff shaking his head. Anybody
else from the public that wishes to
speak on this before we close? Public
comment.
Going once. Going twice. Public comment
is now closed.
Um I believe we had a handful
of of questions. Um I'm trying to think
who would be the the best people to
address them. questions I have notes of
and and maybe one of my commissioners
has other notes. Uh there was a question
about why an apartment would be an
appropriate buffer. Um if as we were
talking about buffers um there's a
question about whether any other there
was any effort to attract other uses.
Um, several comments or questions about
anticipated noise levels
and and one that intrigues me uh has to
do with tying into
uh the inability to tie into the sewer
line that exists in Southwest Drive for
some of the people that live in the
area. Is there somebody from BOPU that
can
clarify what we're talking about if if
we're talking about zoning to tie into a
sewer that nobody can?
>> Yes, sir.
>> Yes. Uh, okay. Frank Strong with the
Cheyenne Board of Public Utilities. We
have not been approached by this
development yet, but have looked at this
parcel in the past. It may require a
lift station depending on their grading,
but it is possible with a lift station
to get in the sewer if need be. Uh
follow-up question. Would a list station
uh provide sewer access to the other uh
land owners, users, residents of the
area if it stole as part of this
>> through you, sir? Yes, that would
provide access to the whole area for
potential sewer access.
>> Thank you. Questions for BOPU from the
commission after comments?
Okay.
Thank you, sir.
Anybody else want to address any of the
the other questions? Staff, the
questions that were raised by the
public.
>> Mr. Chair, this is Seth with Planning
Development. I did want to address a
couple of comments questions that were
brought up. Um, one is that this land
has been zoned MUB in the city limit
since 2010. Um, so we haven't had any
development since then. don't know if
someone's just been sitting on the land
or if there's been active inquiries into
that, but basically since 2010 it's been
silent. So, I don't know if that's once
again, that's just how long it's been
zoned MUB. That's not really uh
indication of how well marketed the land
has been. Um the there's another
question about
um apartments as a transition. Um
generally speaking, single family homes
are considered a lower intensity use,
apartments or town homes are a higher
intensity use. commercial is a even more
intense use and then industrial would be
a more intense use. So on that spectrum,
apartments would be a step between
single family homes and industrial um or
between single family homes and
commercial. Um it's frequently used that
way. Um we did have um some questions
about sound and data centers. Um the LI
zone requires all properties to have no
discernable noise at the property line.
um that's what's written in the UDC. Um
so development on this property um would
have to meet that sound requirement or
would they they would have to seek a
zone change to even more intense zone.
Um I am aware that data centers in
various communities have had cause
problems across the country. Um
certainly a data center in Phoenix uses
a lot more water and cooling than a data
center in Cheyenne. Certainly, we have
data centers. I've seen pictures of them
um towering over residential
neighborhoods
to date in Cheyenne. We haven't had a
data center tower over residential
neighborhood like I've seen in other
places, but it is true that there is no
prohibition on height in LI zone. So, it
could happen at this location if they
chose to build a tall building. Um
uh let's see the there was something
about the protest petition and that is
uh my fault. I should have noted that we
did receive a protest petition. Um, if
valid, it affects third reading at city
council and requires the city council to
have a supermajority. Um, based on the
signatures I saw in that petition, I
have every reason to believe that we
will have a val valid petition by third
reading. However, uh, we need to work
with the city clerk and the city
attorney to make sure that the petition
is legally valid. Um, we would have
concerns about uh accepting a petition
that isn't legally valid and we would
have concerns about um
um not telling someone that their
petition isn't legally valid until a
third reading of of city council. So,
that would be awkward on both ends. So,
we do have a meeting scheduled for this
Friday, which I believe is the earliest
we could get our city attorney and our
city clerk and our city planning
department together to discuss this
protest petition. Um, once again, I have
every reason to believe that it will be
valid by the time we get to third
reading at city council. Um, so that
should be if you want to take that into
consideration on this. Um, it doesn't
affect your vote. Like it doesn't
require you guys to have a unanimous
vote or a supermajority vote, but it is
does exist and it will likely affect
third reading at city council. So, I
should have mentioned that and I
apologize for not mentioning that at
this meeting. Um, I would note just for
everyone present that this is a planning
commission meeting. I think we discussed
this already, but I just want to make
sure everyone knows that pass or fail,
this item goes to city council. Um, so
it will be heard by city council and
they will discuss both the land use map
and the zone change whether it passes or
fails here at the planning commission
meeting. Um, I that's the notes I have
um to discuss. Uh, I'm sure there were
other comments that I've either missed
or cannot answer at this time, but I
those are some of the ones I thought I'm
available for any others. U Mr. Uh,
Director Bloom may also be willing to
answer some of those questions.
>> Director Bloom.
>> Mr. Chair, members of planning
commission, Charles Bloom, planning and
development director. I just wanted to
know one other question or comment I
observed. I wanted to make sure that
everyone understood what it what it
entails. It was in regard to the
Southwest Drive plan that was prepared
by the Metropolitan Planning
Organization. This was a plan that was
prepared in 2024 and it evaluated two
collector streets that intersect with
college drive. One of those being a
major collector street which is
southwest drive which intersects by
Arby's and the fueling center and the
other one was evaluation of broken um
broken arrow which is presently unpaved
and it also intersects. The no planning
study is exactly what it sounds like. It
is a planning study. It is a plan to
evaluate roads and and transportation
corridors that exist today or could
exist in the future. Basically, what it
looked at was what type of roadway could
be designed within the ideal right ofway
for those types of roads. In this case,
they'd both be 80 foot wide collector
roads which typically handle three lane
roads, uh, two travel lanes, uh, turn
lane, shoulders, bicycle lanes, those
items. That plan ultimately was not
approved by the governing body, but it
was basically an evaluation and said
this is something that could happen as
an alternative to what's laid out right
now. Right now, as laid out, any
development that would occur um adjacent
to Southwest Drive or Broken Arrow would
be expected to dedicate the right of way
in con in conjunction with their
development and then improve the roadway
um based on their development. Um, if
there is a development offsite that
would generate a large amount of
traffic, they could be required to
provide off-site improvements to
construct a roadway within those already
predetermined uh corridors.
Uh, the city uh has not pursued eminent
domain for road rightway that I'm aware
of. Um, I am not aware of that happening
um in recent years. nor was eminent
domain ever an item that was discussed
um as a result of that corridor study.
In the event uh that the right of way is
sought for construction, whether it be
by the city or a developer or even the
DOT if they were to be involved or the
uh county government were to be
involved. Um the typical uh method they
use is they purchase the land through
right-of-way acquisition where they um
have an appraisal put together and then
they acquire the land at its current
value. Um eminent domain is is not
something that is wellreceived here in
the state of Wyoming and is not a a
typical path that folks um go through.
So, just want to clarify that that plan
did not uh authorize or detail that any
eminent domain would occur to require
people to give up their land.
Thank you.
>> Thank you. Does any other member of the
commission have questions that they want
addressed that came from public comment?
I did have another question as um Seth
mentioned the sound um LI is no
discernable noise at the property line
but it's well documented and received
and there are a lot of studies coming
out about what they're calling
infrasound um which isn't registered on
a decibel level but it is emitted from
data centers it's a it's a frequency and
it has negative effects on the human
body as well as animals and there's
studies coming out uh I'm not sure that
the city's looked on any of these, but
they're the they're the same places that
are having problem other problems with
data centers. So, Boardman, Oregon,
Newton County, Georgia, Canton,
Mississippi, Mesa, Arizona,
they're all over online. So, um with
these uses and with those sound
barriers, has the city considered,
looked at or have any um remedies for
these
Director Bloom, is that answerable?
>> Mr. Chair and members of the commission,
Charles Bloom, planning development
director. Um, regarding the term
discernable at the property line, that
is what we had our definition. More
recently, we have identified what that
means. uh discernable at the property
line limits the sound adjacent to a
residential development at uh 65 dB and
I believe at in the evening it is down
to it's either it's set is it 60 believe
it's 60 dB in the evening which is
55 it's a little bit um around a casual
conversation um so that's where the
limits are the uh
the infrasound that Commissioner Connor
mentioned. Um that is something that we
have not addressed um in our in our
studies and it's something that we have
seen online but we don't have any data
that is pointing that that is a true
item. Um so we're still evaluating
investigating that.
>> Thank you
>> Mr. Chair. But with that being true,
that would also mean you haven't put a
data center this close to any of any
size and a new one this close to a
residential property. Is that true?
>> Mr. Chair, through you to Commissioner
Connor. Um, regarding data center
entitlements sought by private
developers, there is one that is
proposed um next to the HR ranch is
presently under construction right now.
They went through extensive sound
studies to model their um sound that
would be audible um at the property
lines. Um but that was the limit of
their their stuff was the audio sound.
>> Mr. Chair,
>> this is Seth of Planning and
Development. Um Commissioner Connor, can
you send me the studies you've been
looking at? The only scientifically done
study that I could find regarding
infrasound measured sound and it was
their microphones picked up the sound
from five miles away, but they also
picked up a refrigerator and a
dishwasher that were louder than the
sound of the machines. So, um I'd be
very interested to know what these new
these other studies that you found um
because I have been trying to look at
this and I haven't found the most robust
information. So, please let me know um
so I can look at those as well. Thank
you. Thanks.
>> Thank you. Any other questions?
Anything online? Commissioner Lair,
>> Mr. Chair, through you. I just uh I
guess sort of a combination question for
staff, but but uh tied together. Several
of the commenters
mentioned concerns about impacts to
their water systems and their septic
systems. And one I think mentioned a
concern that uh some of these data
centers might propose to inject
wastewater into the ground an injection
well. Uh is that are those I'm thinking
the water and septic is not a concern
because they will be using city
utilities and I'm thinking we probably
don't allow injection wells. But could
you address that?
>> Mr. Chair, this is Sethway with planning
and development. We do have a
representative from the city engineers
office here, but I believe um our city
engineers uh opinion on this matter is
that the water is not eligible to be uh
discharged into the or onto the earth or
into the earth. Um but I can um Aaron
Gates with their engineering department
may be able to provide more clarity on
that.
>> And Mr. Chair um through you to
Commissioner Leair. Um any injection
well would require a permit by the
Department of Environmental Quality.
they would review that permit. Um they
would evaluate exactly what type of uh
water or any anything would be injected
into that. Um typically anything in the
same limits like that I believe I'm not
just speaking for them. I believe they'd
be hesitant to approve because they
would have an alternative means to
utilize the sanitary sewer system um if
they are discharging it. And in that
case, the board of public utilities does
have standards um as to what um they're
able to accept in their system. Um but
again, this would be a project that
would be on city water service. Um and
also it would, you know, have access to
city sewer service. Um we we do intend
to get some additional information on on
how that would look from DEEQ. Um but
I'll pass on to Erin. Maybe she has some
additional information from the
engineering office.
Thank you. And name and affiliation,
please.
>> Mr. Chair, Aaron Gates, uh, city
engineering. Uh, Director Bloom and Mr.
Lloyd are correct. Uh, these items are
really defined and described by DEEQ as
far as limitations with the underground
injection control program. And I think
uh, the BOP representative can confirm
that as well.
>> Thank you. And I've got one last
question that kind of came up and we
haven't really dwelled on.
Um if if we were to adopt future land
use change to mixed use employment and
then amend to LI
uh what kind of uh light could you I
guess illuminate all of us on on on
lighting restrictions lighting
regulation that would apply were this to
be built out.
>> Mr. Mr. Chair Seth at the planning and
development department. Um, unified
development code 6.4 um is lighting and
it's across all zone districts. So, the
lighting would all have to be shielded
such the light source is not visible
from the property. Um, downward facing
um with the possible exception of some
accent lighting um those sorts of items.
Um and and that would be true whether
it's MUB zoning or LI zoning.
>> Okay. Thank you,
>> Mr. chair three to the members of the
commission. I'd just like to note
regarding the lighting, we have had a
lot of complaints about lighting that
have occurred in the community. A lot of
those complaints are with the data
center construction activities where
there is a requirement for specific
lighting during working hours. Um,
typically when one is done, they are
shielded and they do have very minimal
light pollution that is occurring
because of the downward shielding and
what was noted by Mr. Lloyd. A good
example is looking at some of the data
centers are located in Northr Range
Business Park to the west of the Walmart
distribution center. Those really don't
have much lighting um upon development.
Um we in fact probably have uh most of
our light pollution occurring in the
city is coming from older uh parking
lots and stuff and a lot of unshielded
um lights that do exist in residential
components which frequently aren't um
installed to code.
Thank you. Any other questions before we
move to deliberation?
None.
I will accept a motion from the
commission.
And as a reminder, if if if there the
motion is a negative motion,
we need to specify why. I guess I guess
the first motion that we need to be
discussing is is the application to
amend the future land use map before we
get into the actual zoning. Chair, if if
I may real quick interject. Um, at one
of our more recent meetings, we had a
little bit of a discussion on how a vote
regarding the comprehensive plan is
carried forward to the governing body.
So, I would quickly like just to recap
that real quick. Under state statute, a
land use plan amendment requires a
majority of the commission to vote in
favor of that item. That means four yes
votes regardless of attendance would be
required in order for a statutory
favorable recommendation to move forward
to the governing body. Um however one
other item regarding the bylaws um say
that the chair which is Mr. Wigum here
is only able to vote in the event of a
tie. that means there would have to be a
two two vote and that would trigger his
tie. Um what that means is there's a
potential that a recommendation of say
four uh yes
zero no that would be in compliance with
statute. But if there is a vote that is
three yes and one no technically that is
not a recommendation to approve under
state statute. but it is going to be
forwarded over uh to the governing body
noting that a recommendation to approve
was not statutoily made but there was a
vote of 3 to1 um in favor of this land
use plan amendment or whatever the true
outcome is. So just as a note
procedurally that's how this would move
forward.
Okay. Thank you.
And I am looking for a motion.
We'll look for a motion in a second in
order to discuss.
>> Mr. Chairman, I will read the the motion
as it's written.
Okay. Uh, Commissioner Mthay,
>> I move to approve the resolution
amending the future land use plan for a
portion of land between I80 and the
College Drive east of Southwest Drive as
shown in exhibit A from mixeduse
residential to mixeduse employment. Do
the request meeting the review criteria?
>> I have a motion. Do I have a second?
We can't even discuss this or vote on it
in the absence of a second. Do I have a
second?
I guess the motion fails for lack of a
second.
I will accept
an alternative motion.
>> Mr. Chair, this is Seth with the
planning development department. The
comprehensive plan amendment process
does not require a state of reasons for
denial of a application. So there is no
need to make a denial motion for this.
For the zone change, you will need to
make a denial motion though.
>> Okay. Thank you for the clarification.
>> Okay, Mr.
As staff, we'd like to note the motion
to amend the future land use BAMP um
fails due to lack of a second
>> and then we will move to the zone change
item. Um if you will
>> bear with me, I'll give a brief staff
report on that. And that is due to the
failure of the future land use map
amendment, staff recommends denial of
the zone change.
>> Okay, thank you. And commissioner
director blue
>> chair, Mr. Mr. Chair, members of the
commission, just as a note, regardless
of the outcome of any either of these
items, this item will still move forward
to the uh governing body for
introduction at their meeting on Monday
and then referral to committee, which
will be in two Mondays. Um, and it will
just note the occurrence of the
recommendations here.
Okay.
All I'm looking for a motion on item B
of the agenda. I move to recommend the
governing body deny the reszoning of
approximately 90.5 acres of unplatted
land situated northeast of the
intersection of Broken Arrow Road and
Wooden Shu Drive to LI Light Industrial
as shown in the attached zone change
map, noting that the project does not
meet the review criteria 1 and 8. The LI
zoning request being incompatible with
future land use designation of Mixeduse
residential.
>> It's been moved. Second. Okay, I've got
a second by Commissioner Lair.
Uh, any discussion by the commission?
Amendments?
Hearing? None. Will staff please call
RO?
>> And just a reminder for our commission,
if you support the denial, vote yes.
Please do not vote no.
>> Amy Hernandez,
>> I.
Tony Lair.
>> Hi.
>> Bob Mati.
>> Megan Connor.
>> I.
>> Mr. Chair, that motion passes.
>> Okay. Thank you. Um, we're about two
hours in. Do we need to take a 5 to 10
minute recess for anybody or can we
proceed?
Let's take a five minute recess as the
room clears.
Okay, it's 8 o'clock, so I'd like to uh
call us out of recess and call the
meeting back to order.
Uh, next item up on the agenda is item
D. Will staff please read it into the
record?
>> Item D, PUDC-26-82,
Harmony Valley 24th filing expedited
plat.
Thank you. Do I have an agent for the
applicant here to
tell us what we're looking at?
>> Chair through you, John Sers's agent for
True Great Land Development. What you
have before is a subdivision plat for an
approved site plan uh for 524 unit plex
over off of college and parsley that was
previously approved with that in order
to make the sales capabilities for each
individual building for ownership. Um we
are asking for a six lot subdivision
being five lots for each individual
building. The six lot will actually be a
one in six or one in five interest for
the six lot to go ahead and pay for open
space and common space area. Um staff
has through building department and
engineering and BOP approved the site
plan. We do have a green stamp on it.
This is just a formality to go ahead and
develop the land itself. And I stand for
any questions.
>> Thank you. Any questions for the
applicant from the commission?
hearing none. Will staff please present
the staff report.
>> Okay,
>> Mr. Chair, Mr. Chair, Morgan Dennis,
Planning and Development. Um, this is an
expedited plat for 6.5 acres of land
located east of South Parsley Boulevard
and north of West College Drive. The lot
is currently vacant. The purpose of this
plat is to create the common lot and
five individual lots for the building.
Um responsibility of maintenance for the
common lot will be split into 15
interest for each building owner. They
will be responsible for maintaining the
common lot
to the approved site plan. The parcel is
currently undergoing the site plan
process.
A future land use map designates this
area as mixeduse commercial. This parcel
recently undergone a zoning change from
Harmony Valley PUB to the NR3 zone. All
multi-dwelling building lot types are
allowed within the NR3 zone. Um the lots
proposed are reflective of buildings on
the approved site plan and are buildable
in the NR3 zone. After meeting all
review criteria, staff recommends
approval and I stand for questions.
Okay. Any questions for staff?
>> Mr. Chair, I have a question.
>> Uh, Commissioner Ma.
>> Yes. I just wonder for the the I guess
the fifth lot that's going to be or the
the extra lot that's going to be divided
between the other five five lots and
it's going to be the the uh
responsibility of the five to maintain
that sixth lot. If they do not do that,
does the city have any kind of uh
ability to force them to take care of
the lot?
>> Mr. Trau, uh Conor White Planning
Development Department. Yes. So, because
this property has a site plan um that
basically covers the entirety of the
lot, should any landscaping, maintenance
or anything of that sort basically fall
into poor conditions, it can become a
zoning violation that the city can then
issue um basically to all five of the
other uh owners. So that is how we would
enforce this through the zoning
violation for maintenance because it
does it has basically a site plan that
goes along with project
Mr. Chair through you. Would that mean
you would put a lean on the other five
property owners or or what would happen?
>> Mr. Chair, through you. Um so a lean
wouldn't be something we jump to right
away. Um, basically the zoning violation
process would start basically telling
them they're out of compliance and that
they need to fix it. Uh, through our
zoning violation process, we do have the
ability to abate the process or
basically abate and we could technically
by code go in replant everything and put
a lean on the property.
And I guess as a followup and does that
include being able to do things like
promptly mow and clean up and then
proceed with enforcement
through your abatement or do we have to
wait for that process to conclude before
we actually fix the problem?
>> Mr. Chair through you. So it go through
the process to basically um we would
have to issue basically a letter that
says we're going to abate the property
go out abate and then we'd lean the
property. Um, when it comes to like
mowing grass and stuff, compliance
already does things like that. When it
comes to uh weeds, junk, grass, they do
actually they have done that in the
past. When it comes to properties that
do not uh comply, um they hire some sort
of landscaping company to go out there,
mow the grass, and then they will
basically lean the property or charge
that property owner for that fee.
>> Thank you. Any other questions from
commission?
Any
follow-up questions from uh to the
applicant?
I'll open this up for public comment. Is
there anybody from the public who wishes
to speak on this item,
ma'am?
>> Heather Madrid. I live in Harmony
Meadows.
We need sidewalks on College Drive. Um
there's no there's no safe way for kids
to get to school from all this
development that's happening in that
area. Um the speed limit on college is
50 miles per hour which through what is
now a residential neighborhood. Um this
will just expand that residential
neighborhood further up college.
And I think that it should be not even
an option for developers to not consider
the safety of children when there are so
many schools in this area. and
presumably going to be a lot of kids
moving in. Um, so that would be my only
question, comment, concern with this
ongoing development of this area.
There's just like not a lot of safety
taken into consideration with this.
>> Okay, thank you. Any other members of
the public present that wish to comment
on this item?
Any
other members of the public Zoom land
that wish to comment?
Public comment going once, going twice.
Public comment is now closed.
Um would the applicant please come
forward?
Would
you care to address please address the
sidewalks question as as the applicant I
believe knows this is an issue near and
dear to my heart
>> Mr. chair through you John Sers agent
for True Grit. So that the statement's
incorrect. I I need to clear some things
up from Waltershide
past u the elementary school that is a
30 mph zone. Immediately after the elev
or the elementary school up to Grand
Harmony Boulevard just past Triumph in
the middle of there the speed limit
jumps from 30 to 40 miles an hour. The
reason we know this is that during our
study for doing Harmony Valley fifth
filing was whether or not a deceleration
lane needs to be put in at this time. It
does not need to be put in at York
turning in at this point. Um from
York up further to Danny Place right in
there in between Danny Place or I'm
sorry York and LCG the speed limit does
jump to 50 mph up in that area. Um
what's not being represented is that
when uh the Grand Harmony Apartments
complex was being constructed near uh
Harmony Meadows, um the city staff
actually asked us to go ahead and finish
the sidewalk that was non-existent from
Greenway Commons over to our property
line. And then we took that as well and
brought that all the way around the
property up and through Grand Harmony
Boulevard. What's also worth noting is
up on Grand Harmony Boulevard uh to our
north, there was no sidewalk for that
area as well. So staff and us worked
together that we actually put sidewalk
in from our north boundary line on Grand
Harmony Boulevard up to Center One Drive
and cleared up that intersection. Uh
it's also worth noting that the sidewalk
along College from Triumph over to York
was put in over u hasn't been stretched
but from York up has been. The reason
the sidewalk hasn't been put in from
Triumph to York at this time period is
strictly because one the white dot
concern of how they may take over the
road. Number two with that though is
that parcel in front of our property or
the detention pond there is questionable
of what is to be done. So by putting in
the pathway at this exact second which
isn't a requirement hinders what we can
and cannot do by spending money and
wasting that time for other things. The
sidewalk from York has been run all the
way up to Danny Place as a matter of
fact and then on to LCG. There is a
project from the city side that is
supposed to release in 2028 that takes
the greenway commons from the
intersection of LCG or Carolan and York
further up to Cribbon and that is part
of the project for the city to extend
York up to Cribbon. As pointed out when
we went through Harmony Valley 23rd
filing, which was recently approved in
final plat, there is sidewalks that are
attached in that subdivision that
actually get them back up to Allison
Road. As was discussed during that
meeting, we have no ties to Waltershide
Boulevard and that is a city question as
well in regards to how that access and
sidewalk along Walteride. That's outside
our spectrum and scope. I think that
takes care of all your questions unless
you have a follow-up.
Any
other questions of the applicant from
the commission?
Yeah, thank you.
I'm looking for a motion, I think.
>> Can I just say one more thing about
that?
>> Um, a public comment is closed. I I'm
really curious what you have to say, but
we close public comment.
>> Okay. When would be a good opportunity
to express the concern? I live there and
I can assure you it is unsafe.
>> Um, this is a recommendation. I believe
it'll be before the city council that
has more teeth than we do.
Um,
>> thank you.
>> I How many weeks
in two weeks? But that I assume will
just be an introduction and referral to
committee.
>> Mr. Chair, through you uh Conor Way plan
development department. So there'll be
introduction next Monday and then
discussion the following Monday. Final
consideration the Monday after that.
>> Oh, so two weeks will be when it's
>> two weeks will actually be support
committee for discussion.
>> Which is the best time to
>> Yes, that'll be June 15th I believe.
>> Okay. Thank you,
>> Mr. Chair. Commissioner Lair. I move to
approve the Harmony Valley 24th filing
preliminary plat advancing the final
plat to the governing body.
>> Second.
>> It's been moved and seconded. Any
discussion, comment by the commission?
Hearing none. Will staff please call
roll.
Bob Mia.
>> Yes.
Tony Lur. Hi. Megan Connor.
>> Hi.
>> Amy Hernandez.
>> I.
>> Mr. Chair, that motion passes.
>> Okay. Thank you.
Staff, please read item E into the
record.
>> Item E, PUDC-26-83,
Swan Ranch Rail Park 20th filing,
assigned zoning.
And M. Chair, I should note their staff
is technically the applicant on this one
because it's an assigned zoning.
>> Please present the report.
>> Chair, members of committee, Conor Way,
Planning and Development Department, um
the project before you, it's an assigned
zoning. So, as was noted um at the
beginning of the meeting with assigned
zonings, they basically go along with
annexations. Um but there isn't any
discussion on the annexation with this
item. It's all about what staff
recommends it be assigned once it's
annexed.
So, the parcel that you have um before
you for the assigned zoning is northwest
of the intersection of Clear Creek
Parkway and Ganet Peak Drive. This is
out in the Swan Ranch Rail Park on the
west side of town.
This property is currently zoned um LI
out in the county. So, it is county LI.
So looking at the area which is either
LII or some sort of industrial uh
planned unit development
um and also looking at uses on this area
which are all industrial in nature.
Staff does recommend that uh the
assigned zoning be
with upon its annexation. Uh that is the
best fit for the property. That's what
it's already zoned in the county and
that's what the area basically already
has.
So with that, staff does recommend um
approval of this assigned zoning to
assign the property to light industrial
upon its annexation. And I am available
for any questions.
Okay. Thank you. Any questions of staff
from the commission?
Hearing none, I'll open this up for
public comment. Are there any members of
the public uh present who wish to
comment on this matter?
Seeing none, are there any members of
the public on Zoomland that wish to
comment?
Public comment going once, going twice.
Public comment is now closed.
Any questions? I guess we've we've dealt
with that. I'm looking for a motion from
the commission.
I move to recommend the governing body
approve the assigned zoning for land
northwest of the intersection of Clear
Creek Parkway and Ganet Peak Drive to LI
Light Industrial as shown in the
attached zone chain change map, noting
that the project meets the re review
criteria for approval.
>> Okay, thank you. I've got a motion. Do I
have a second?
>> Second.
>> It's been moved by Commissioner Connor
and seconded by Commissioner Ma.
Um any discussion
on this at the commission hearing? None.
Will staff please call roll.
>> Where am I? Amy Hernandez
>> I.
>> Tony Lair.
>> I Megan Connor
>> I.
>> Bob Matio
>> Mr. Chair that motion passes.
>> Okay. Thank you. Will staff please read
item F into the record?
>> Item F, PUDC-26-87,
Swan Ranch Rail Park 21st filing
expedited plat.
>> Okay, thank you. Do we have an agent for
the applicant
here that wants to tell us what's going
on with Swan Ranch Rail Park 21st
filing?
Oh, over here.
>> Uh, good evening, commissioners, uh,
members of the board. My name is Mark
Christensen. I am with AVIPC.
We are at 1103 Oldtown Lane. Um, and we
are acting as the agent for the
applicant. Um, so this item is before
you with the expedited plat
uh, the subject parties properties for
development. Um, so as you can see, it
is changing uh, three unplatted lats
lots into four developable lots. um and
the Swan Range Swan Ranch Business Park,
excuse me. Um so these are uh proposed
as you'll see in the following item to
be with the BP zone. Um so anticipating
industrial type uses um looking at the
BP zone largely because it grants more
flexibility. Um one hallmark of the BP
zone is that it must be at least 320
acres of contiguity. Um which is the
reason for the BP zone at this time. So,
we have strung together some other
properties that have already been
platted in that BP zone. Um, but this is
for those specific lots in the Swan
Ranch Business Park um for industrial
type uses. And I'm available for any
questions.
>> Okay. Thank you. Are there any questions
of the applicant from commissioners?
Anything from the commissioners online?
Um, I've got a quick question. Do we
have any kind of idea
what you're trying to accomplish with
these additional lots and and zoning?
What new uses are we looking at?
>> Yes, chair you to the members of the
commission. So, the impetus for this was
um some interest in data center
development on the larger parcel.
However, there are other property other
potential uses that could go on this
subject property. Um the main
consideration here is that um I guess
it's with the zone change the the uses
um are expanded with the BP zone. So um
a data center is already allowed in the
alli zoning which it already is. Uh but
the BP zoning would allow further uses
such as um some retail uh food service
type uses that are allowed in the BP
zone that aren't permitted outright in
the LI zone.
>> Okay. Thank you.
And will staff please
read in the report
or provide the report.
Chair and members of the commission
Connor White Planning Development
Department. So the area before you uh
very similar area to what we just talked
about with the assigned zoning. It
actually does incorporate the assigned
zone parcel. So this project is located
west of I25 and north of Wallik uh west
wall.
the property um one of the I guess two
of the properties in question. The one
with the assigned zoning should have
come in and be annexed to be assigned
the LI zone would um currently have the
LI zone designation. Obviously we there
was a little mention of the next item
which is the zone change to BP. Um but
current zoning out there is LI for the
larger parcel and then the parcels that
are across Clear Creek are currently
zoned community business.
uh future land use map. This whole area
is mixeduse employment. There's a slight
sliver of open space out there. Um
it's mostly just a remnant at this point
out in that area. Uh it kind of followed
what the PUD that is out there kind of
in intended for, but that PUD was never
developed to what it was actually kind
of written for. So most of this area
though is industrial in nature is on the
future land use map as mixeduse
employment.
The applicant is proposing um a plat for
roughly 233.33
acres of land. Proposed plat would
create uh four lots for industrial and
commercial development.
Uh, as I mentioned, there is a proposed
zone change, uh, which is the next item
on the agenda to the business park zone.
With this plat, it does incorporate a
parcel that is, uh, proposed to be
annexed and then does dedicate an
extension of street that extends out
west and provides some connectivity to
potential future development uh, to the
western area.
It does take one lot that's across Clear
Creek Parkway does divide it into two
and then it is taking the larger lot
which is an already platted lot. Um it
is currently platted as a remainder lot.
So the only way a remainder lot can be
developed, sold off, anything like that.
It does have to be replplatted. That
could have been done administratively.
Um but with this they are choosing to
add some additional land with that
street to the north which is why that is
coming before you. So, as the applicant
mentioned, um there's the potential for
data center development. I do want to
make it clear a data center can already
develop on this parcel without even
coming before this body or city council.
Um
with this plat major thing here is
combining a couple of also kind of
remnant lots that were at one point
railroad um proposed for railroad that
are on the western side of the parcel.
uh that does clean that up and brings
them into the larger lot
through the review. Um
this whole area is large lot
development. Um it all it is is all
industrial in nature. Um block size is
something that doesn't get looked at
when it comes to industrial parks. Uh
because industrial parks do allow for or
industrial zoning because it does allow
for larger lots. Um
there was a drainage and traffic
worksheet. Both of those were reviewed.
There were no concerns at this um at the
platting level. More in-depth review
will be done uh when site plans are
proposed for the actual development of
the lots.
As I mentioned, there is the road that
is being proposed. Um it lines up with
Ganet Peak on the east side and then
connects over and goes across to provide
potential future connections uh further
to the west
through the review. Um I should note
that in the staff report I have the
wrong um exception and
the wrong uh condition at the end of the
staff report. So I actually have the
correct one on the screen.
um on the final slide, but basically the
only condition that staff would put on
this plat would be that any technical
corrections be finalized and corrected
prior to recording of the plat.
Otherwise, through staff's review, staff
does recommend approval. And with that,
I'm available for any questions.
Okay. Thank you. Questions for staff
from the commission?
Hearing none, I'll open this item up for
public comment. Are there anybody Is
anybody from the public here that wants
to comment on this?
Anybody in Zoomland
online?
Okay.
Uh, if there's somebody there, please
state your name and address for the
record.
>> Can you hear me?
>> Yes.
>> Charles Miller, Laramie County. Um, I
just have a uh Mr. Mr. Chair,
commissioners, for the record. Um,
I uh I have a direct question for the
applicant and for staff. Um,
and overall, uh, I guess I' I'd like it
on the record. Um,
by changing this zoning from light
industrial, is that correct? You guys
are changing it from light industrial to
business park.
>> Yes.
>> Um, okay. Does
>> point of order, that's the next item, I
believe, chairman. Um, does this
designation allow allow for the project
to bypass the Wyoming Industrial Sitting
Council permitting process?
>> Under state law, large industrial
projects normally must go through the
industrial sitting council, which
requires public hearings and impact
mitigation for roads, water, services in
the community. However, locating inside
a designated business park often exempts
these projects from that review. So,
will reszoning this property to business
park allow you to claim an exemption
from the full industrial city council
review and associated mitigation
requirements?
>> Hello.
>> Um, we'll collect your uh the questions
and address address questions at the
end.
>> Okay. Thank you. Um,
>> for clarification, we're not reszoning
here. We're we're drawing lines on a map
for the parcels, but go ahead.
>> Okay. Okay. And then uh here's my
question too. Um if you're exempt from
that state oversight, are you willing to
uh sign a binding development agreement
with the city that voluntarily provides
the same level of environmental
monitoring, water usage reporting, noise
studies, including infr infrasound, and
impact fees that the state process would
have required. Third question, can you
confirm on the record that this zoning
change grants no exemptions from federal
EPA rules on aquafer protection,
wastewater injection, or air quality
permits from backup gener generators.
Um,
uh,
I urge you, um, to to look at all these
things. I I I understand I may be a
little bit uh, out of sequence here. So,
um, that's all I have for now. Thank
you.
Okay, thank you. Are there any other qu
uh comments from the public
hearing? None. Seeing none, public
comment is now closed.
Um, as a reminder, I guess I messed up a
little bit. Those questions seem to be
addressed to the next item.
Um,
are there any
does anybody want to address any of the
the open issues
questions from from com uh the
commission to the applicant or staff?
>> Mr. Chair, if I may, I can address some
of the questions that we did hear real
quick.
>> Um, regarding the question regarding
industrial sighting division sighting,
sit t i n. Um this is with an existing
business park so it is exempt from the
industrial sighting committee processes.
Um regarding a development agreement um
that is a that is not a requirement of
the city. That is something completely
at the discretion of the land owner. Um
I don't see the relevancy with that in
regard to this subdivision of land. And
the other item was in regard to any
necessary permits regarding state um
agencies. And uh nothing here would
exempt them from any necessary permits
that are required by the state whether
it be through the state engineers
office, department of environmental
quality or any other studies that they
would be required to do outside of our
process.
>> Okay. Thank you,
>> Mr. Chair. Uh Commissioner Lair
>> through you. Just a followup for
Director Bloom. Um,
when you say this is within an existing
business park, are you talking
generically a business park versus the
business park zoning that's in the next
item?
>> Mr. Chair, through you to Commissioner
Lair, that's a great question. Um, so
often has the business park zone
district, which now we look at that that
probably wasn't the best name of a zone
district. Now it gets confused with a
business park which could be organized
through a property owners association
and other ways like that. So this is
within what is recognized as a business
park regardless of its zoning. This
business park has different zonings. It
has CB community business. It has LI. It
has um agriculture I believe. and it
also has a plan unit development um
that's outside of the city. So, it has a
variety of different zone districts in
this business this recognized business
park area.
Okay. Thank you. Any other questions
from the commission?
Hearing none. I'm looking for a motion.
I move to approve the Swan Ranch Rail
Park 21st filing preliminary plat
advancing the final plat to the
governing body with staff recommended
conditions.
Okay. Is there a second?
>> Second.
>> Thank you. It's been seconded by
Commissioner Connor. Any discussion by
the council
hearing? None. Staff, please call roll.
>> Bob Mia,
>> I.
>> Tony Lair,
>> Megan Connor,
>> I.
>> Amy Hernandez,
>> Mr. Chair, that motion passes. Okay.
Thank you. And now we're move on to item
H, which is the
No, we're going to move on to item G,
which is the zoning map amendment. Will
will staff, please read it into the
record.
>> Item G, PUDC-26-86,
Swan Ranch Rail Park zoning map
amendment.
Okay. And can we please have it agent
for the applicant?
Yes, cheer through you. Uh my name is
Mark Christensen. I am with AVIPC at
1103 Oldtown Lane. Um so this is the
item before you with the the business
park zoning. So um I think you can blame
me a little bit for jumping the gun on
the last one. Apologies on that. Uh but
the business park zone is really to um
incite sort of conducive development. Um
I brought this up while uh we were
discussing the last item. Uh but the the
BP business park zone integrates uh
commercial services more along with the
industrial uses that could be already
located in the LI district. So this
includes um the it from the code it says
the district integrates manufacturing,
processing, research and development and
shipping activities in addition to
retail, dining and convenience stores.
So um it goes beyond the LI zone with
the in addition to those retail dining
and convenience stores. Um again it is
required to have 320 acres minimum which
is why it is before you now. Um as
director Bloom had previously said it is
in a business park association. So that
is not to be confused with the the
business park zone. Uh with that I'm
available for any questions.
>> Okay. Do we have any questions for the
applicant?
I have a question. Um, Mr. Connor,
>> um,
ju just looking at the map, it looks a
little bit peacemeal. Are there any, um,
objections from anyone surrounding there
or is anyone else looking to join this
business park?
See a lot of connectivity in it. They
just kind of disjointed it.
Uh so chair throughou with this being a
uh landowner initiated resoning we we
have just acted on the behalf of the
land owner. Um we we did not request the
the other properties to be in at this
time. Um like likely because some of
those are already developed and wouldn't
really need to be reszoned. Um so that
that could be a potential reason for it.
Um if it were a city initiated resoning
there might be some more properties
including it. Uh however, we have only
initiated this on behalf of uh the land
owner who has uh the LLC's that are
listed on the application.
>> Thank you. Any further questions,
follow-ups?
>> Thank you. Staff, will you please
provide your report?
Chair, members of the uh commission,
Connor White, Planning and Development
Department.
So again, very similar area that we're
looking at. Um it's kind of going from
one small property to now larger
properties um in that order. Uh so same
area we're located north of uh basically
north and south of West Wall Road and
west of I25.
Again, uh much of this area on the
future land use map, it's already
mixeduse employment. And then the
existing zoning within the proposed area
for the zone change is either light
industrial community business or um
basically an industrial PUD that's out
there. Uh that industrial PUD is
basically a heavy industrial PUD. So it
basically allows any of the uses allowed
in an heavy industrial zone district.
Um,
looking at the BP zone,
like Director Bloom had said, this this
has been coming up quite a bit with the
confusion between what is a business
park by association versus zoning. Um,
the way to think about the zoning is we
could have called this the industrial
flex zone rather than the business park
zone. So, again, that's kind of might be
staff's fault for kind of calling it
business park at this point. Um, but it
could have just been called industrial
flex. It's basically zoning does not um
zoning doesn't bypass other state and
federal requirements. Um,
those still have to be abided by as
director Bloom said. Um, the the zone
district is very different than the
business park association portion.
So with this, the applicant is
requesting uh to reszone roughly 394.7
acres of land uh to the BP business park
zone district. Um pretty much all this,
actually not pretty much, all of this
land is vacant land currently. Um again,
it's all either zoned light industrial
community business or it's the Swan
Ranch Rail Park planned unit
development.
Um this area out here um as stated as
well is all industrial by nature.
There's either um industrial
warehousing. You do have some RV sales
that are across within the smaller kind
of overland trails business park area.
Uh there's kind of more heavier
industrial as you go south.
The BP zone is meant to be a combination
of the LICB and HI zone district. So it
does allow for that flexibility in
varying uses. Does allow for more
commercial uses than the LI zone. Does
allow many more uses than what the PUB
allows. Um and then it allows maybe some
more intense uses than the CB zone uh
that is currently out there along I25.
Also, as mentioned by the applicant,
this was or basically owner initiated.
So, this is not a city initiated one.
Um, they can only act on those that
owners have uh requested to be part of
the zone zone change. Should the zone
change be approved and um be approved by
council as well and become effective, if
other properties do want to join the
business park zone district and they are
adjacent to what gets reszoned, they
will have that opportunity to do so in
the future.
Based on the review criteria and the the
fact that this is an industrial area, uh
staff does recommend approval of the
zoning map amendment and I'm available
for any questions.
>> Okay. Thank you. Any questions of staff
from the commission? Commissioner Lair.
>> Mr. Chair through you. Hi. I'm just
curious since the city did initiate the
large zone change to BP for the uh two
business parks to the east.
Have you considered doing that for this
particular business park, the the whole
of it or most of it?
Chair through you. Um
there's been there there's been
discussions. Um, the biggest thing with
why we did the other business park is
that business park was already so hard
to get property owners with the 320
acres that were adjacent to each other.
This one does have a land owner that has
majority of the land where they can
initiate it themselves.
Obviously, also it takes staff time to
do these resonings if staff was to
initiate them. There's probably plenty
of resonings we would love to do. Um,
but comes down to staff time. I mean,
you can see what the agenda looks like
tonight. Um, our department's been
pretty busy. So, doing city initiated or
staff initiated ones we've discussed,
but if an applicant wants and has the
land requirement to be able to do it
themselves and they want to do it more
quickly, they're probably going to need
to uh rather than waiting for staff to
get around to doing it. But again, there
there's been discussions, but nothing
concrete of yes, staff is going to
reszone this whole area.
Mr. Chair, and I'd just like to add real
quick,
>> director,
>> Mr. Mr. Chair, I'd like to add real
quick that there is an inherent
difference with this this industrial
area compared to the one out on camp
stool um road, Shyan Business Parkway.
This is within a plan unit development
that has some uh different development
standards that are spelled out in the
plan unit development. So, the change
wasn't uh hadn't risen to a point where
needed to be done. I've been working
with a couple developments uh in the uh
camp stool business park, the shine
business um parkway area. Um it was
noted that some of the
um development standards needed um
adjustment for some developments. I use
one example which is the um Eagleclaw
facility which um had a lot of uh
landscaping that is not beneficial for
the overall area for future phases.
Okay, thank you. And just for
clarification for the record, the point
of this attempt to reszone is to make it
so we don't need to do multiple reszones
as different lots have different ideas
in the future. We're hoping to see this
is the last reszoning in this area.
>> Mr. Chair, that would be correct because
again, the BP zone is that mix of three
different zone districts with a lot a
lot of varying uses. So, similar to what
staff had kind of said with the last
business, the one that we had brought
forward, it's kind of hopefully the last
time you have to see a reszone for these
lots because they should have a
significant amount of uses that they're
able to put on property rather than
going LI to CB or CB to HI or, you know,
back and forth. Okay. Thank you.
Further questions? We'll open this up
for public comment. Is there any member
of the public here who wishes to speak
on this item?
Public comment
is okay. Okay. Uh public comment via
Zoom.
>> Charles Miller, you should be able to
unmute yourself.
>> Can you hear me?
>> Yes, sir.
>> Okay. Okay, Charles Miller. Um, sorry.
Uh, give me just a second here. I got my
uh my notes I'm pulling up here. Um, is
this is the uh item number G. Is that
correct?
>> Yes.
>> Um, and that's for the Swan Ranch Rail
Park amendment. Um, it looks like uh
that on page four of your PUDC 2686
uh that you're changing this to be a
business park because of the difficulty
of creating traditional urban blocks. It
just seems funny to me if the developer
doesn't want to follow the city's
subdivision design standards, uh, we
just change the zone for them to make it
easier. I mean, it just seems a little
strange there. Uh and then there's uh
this table on the future land use map.
It clearly says the designation for this
site is mixeduse employment/open
space. But if you approve this business
park reszone for all 394.7
acres, um the open space just vanishes.
Poof. Um I guess I'm just a little
confused how uh we can just ignore the
open space protections in Plan Cheyenne
like that. Um,
uh, oh, one more thing. Uh, I was, um, I
was wondering about the Wyoming
Industrial, uh, Sighting Council. Uh
it
uh can you talk more maybe about the
um the
permitting from the state uh for a large
industrial projects um that that
normally has to take place but but that
the exemptions that the business park
zoning uh um provides. Thank you. That's
all I've got.
Hey, thank you. Is there anybody else
from the public who wishes to speak on
this item?
Anybody online?
Hearing none. Public comment going once,
going twice. Public comment is now
closed.
Um, I guess there was a question in
there
uh regarding
the relevance of of our of our zoning
and the
sighting council permitting process or
is the answer any different than the
previous item?
>> Mr. Chair, Charles Bloom playing
director. Um, not much of a difference
in answer. I urge them to have any
questions regarding another agency's
process to contact that agency.
>> Okay. Thank you.
With that, any other questions from the
commission?
I am looking for a motion.
Mr. Chair, I
>> Commissioner Lair,
>> I move to recommend the governing body
approve the reszoning of lots four and
five, block three, Swan Ranch Rail Park
8 filing, lots 7, 8, 11, 12, 13, 14, and
15, block two and lot nine, block one,
Swan Ranch Rail Park 11th filing. Tract
A, Swan Ranch Rail Park 18th filing.
Tract one, Swan Ranch Rail Park 20th
filing, lots one and two, block three,
Swan Ranch Rail Park 21st filing to BP
Business Park as shown in the attached
zone change map, noting that the project
meets the review criteria for approval.
>> Thank you. Yeah, I've got a I have a
motion. Is there a second?
>> Second.
>> It's been seconded by Commissioner Mth.
Any discussion by the commission?
Hearing none. Will staff please call
roll.
Tony Lair.
>> Hi.
>> Amy Hernandez.
>> No.
>> Megan Connor.
Bob Mati
>> I
and Boyd Wiggle
>> I. Mr. Chair, that motion passes.
Okay. Item eight. Will staff that please
read item H into the record?
>> Item H PUDC-26-84
Highlands assigned zoning. Again, Mr.
Chair I city is the applicant. I know I
have an agent on the agenda but
>> I was going to ask about that.
>> City is the applicant on this one.
>> Would staff please present the report.
>> Chair and members commission counterway
planning and development department.
Again with any assigned zoning um this
basically goes along with annexation.
As always stated, we're here to talk
about the assigned zoning, not the
annexation. That gets discussed at
council.
The area that we're looking at, it is
located east of South Gley Highway and
south of the Sweetgrass subdivision.
The area we are looking at um is for um
an annexation of
3,459.99
acres of land. Um
this whole area is zoned LU, so land use
out in the county. Uh the LU zone does
allow for various
basically uses. Um especially on large
properties, they can get conditional use
for
lots of varying items, whether it be uh
gravel quaries. Um there are oil fields
already out in this area. Um I think
even which with large property like this
that could have a conditional use for
data center in the LU. Um
staff looking at the surrounding area
and even the size of the land. Um Steph
is recommending that the assigned zoning
be to AG agricultural.
So upon annexation it would be assigned
the AG agricultural zone. Um and then
any further reszoning or development
would require basically additional
applications.
I'm sure everybody has seen the agenda.
There is two items that will come after
this one with applicant requested future
land use map amendment and a uh
applicant requested zone change.
with this assigned zoning. Again, after
reviewing uh the surrounding zoning, the
current use of the property, the just
overall size of the area, staff does
recommend that uh the assigned zoning be
to AG agricultural.
With that, I am available for any
questions.
Are there any questions of staff from
the commission?
Hearing none, I will open this item up
for public comment. Are there any
members of the public who wish to speak
on present who wish to speak on this
item?
Yes, ma'am.
>> Heather Madrid, Harmony Meadows. My
question with this is
I mean I have a lot of questions but I'm
going to try to stay away from the whole
annexation thing but I don't understand
why we're treating this 33,400
plus acre
um request the same as
the previous which was still huge 300
over 300 acres and the same even still
as a 90 acre uh request for a
reasonzoning of property that isn't even
annexed yet into the city. Um
that is I am I am positive that is not
the intent of any of our current laws or
regulations.
Um also it's already been publicly um
shared what the intent of this land will
be. It's not agricultural. So my
question is why would we
with knowing full well that this is
going to be a massive data center
complex? Why would we reszone or why
would anybody reszone it to
agricultural? uh seems like a very
intentional misrepresentation
of the intent um and is kind of in line
with and and and worsening this idea
that there is not um transparency and
it's led to panic quite frankly and
extreme hypervigilance within the public
to even be willing to argue for almost
two hours over landscaping.
Um,
this is very concerning to me. This
isn't this isn't a little bit of land.
And it also um the final intended use of
this is actually not even remotely
aligned with the future land use map,
which is from my understanding again uh
grossly outdated. So, I don't know why
we continue to rely on that map for
these massive, massive annexations and
projects that are, as someone stated
earlier, locking the city in and
preventing future growth in a diverse
way. Thank you.
>> Okay. Thank you. Is there anybody else
present who wishes to comment item?
Seeing none, are there is there anybody
via Zoom who wishes to comment?
Public comment going once, going twice.
Public comment is now closed.
Uh will
I guess uh the questions I heard would
staff please address the the purpose of
this this assigned zoning that we're
talking about to recap that Mr. Chair
through you. So basically a little bit
of process here um
we have with any annexation
there's always an assigned zoning.
Annexation does not get discuss
discussed at planning commission.
Annexation goes straight to council, but
staff ended up um I want to say it was a
year or two ago, we developed the
assigned zoning to basically give a
property that's annexed its base zone
district. Uh once it's annexed, if we
don't have that base zone district, the
property has no zone district, which
means it has no regulation. We did
actually have that happen at one point
prior to having assigned zoning
um because the zone change request from
the applicant failed at council.
So now we have assigned zoning where
basically with any annexation staff
reviews what the current use of the land
is, what the current area looks like, uh
what the basically looking at
surrounding zoning and staff recommends
basically a base zone district to give
the person.
In this case, the base zone district
staff recommends is agricultural. Now,
if the applicant doesn't like that zone
district because it doesn't allow them
to develop on it, then they also submit
an application from them requesting it
be reszoned to a zone district that they
would like. Those are the next two items
on the agenda. Um, the next two items
are the future land use map amendment
for this same area and a zoning map
amendment to the business park zone
district for this area.
So,
this is the process that we've always
gone through with these. uh there always
is an assigned zoning with annexation.
As you can see with the first item on
the agenda, there was no proposed zone
change from that um applicant. They're
residential property. They don't need
anything different than the AR zone. So,
they're going with the assigned zoning.
In this case, there are two more items
that follow this. Yes, I know it's been
made um made public that this is for a
data center. Um there are
representatives here and that will be
part of probably their presentation when
we get to it with the next two items.
But for this specific item, we are just
talking about what is the base zone
district upon annexation. This land
could still be annexed and assigned the
agricultural zone and then council could
maybe choose not to approve the next two
items.
It's annexed and has the AG zone. And
then at that point
um anything that gets annexed has to
have a zone district. So that is what
this application or this discussion is
for.
And I guess as a followup, cross-examine
a little bit and and and to be clear,
does this if we approve this and the the
five plus square miles does not actually
get annexed to the city, does this have
any legal effect? If the annexation
fails,
>> Mr. Chair, if the annexation fails, this
would also fail. Um, basically if
council does not approve the annexation
on third reading, I would probably get
up and tell them you also need to not
approve the next three items on the
agenda because they are all tied to the
annexation.
>> So the order basically the order of
operation at council would be
annexation, assigned zoning, future land
use map amendment, zone change. That
would be basically the order that these
items would be uh for third reading. I
can't guarantee that's how they're going
to be discussed on
agendas prior to um but for final
consideration and final approvals that
would be the order they would need to be
in.
>> Okay,
any other questions
of staff from the commission
hearing? None.
I'm looking for a motion.
Mr. Chairman,
I move to recommend the governing body
approve the assigned zoning for land
east of South Gley Highway and south of
the sweet sweetg grass development to AG
agriculture as shown in the attached
zone change map. Noting that the project
meets the review criteria for approval.
Thank you. Do I have a second?
>> Second.
>> It's been seconded by Commissioner Lair.
Any discussion by the commission?
>> Hearing none, will staff please call
roll.
>> Amy Hernandez,
>> yes.
Megan Connor
>> I
>> Tony Lair
>> I Mr. Chair that motion passes.
>> Okay. Thank you.
And I understand that the next two items
are going to be discussed again together
again much like the previous.
Okay. Staff, please read items I and J
into the record. We'll discuss those and
then we'll hold two separate votes on
them.
>> Item I, PUDC-26-116,
Highlands future land use map amendment
and item J is PUDC-26-85
Highlands zoning map amendment.
>> Okay, we have an agent for the
applicant. Uh chairman, planning
commission members, Brad Emmens, AVI,
11:03 Oldtown Lane, uh number 101 here,
uh representing the owner, Arpan Hammond
Hardware Company, Old Horse Pasture
Incorporated, and Lumus Livestock
Company, who are the current owners of
the property that have submitted this uh
land use application and zone change.
With me, I'm going to turn it over to
Rachel Orwing first. she wants to would
like with Microsoft to give a
presentation and then uh I continue my
uh stuff after that.
>> Thank you P.
>> Welcome.
>> Good evening chair, members of the
planning commission staff and members of
the public. My name is Rachel Irwing. I
serve as the land development and
permitting program manager for
Microsoft. Our address is uh one
Microsoft way, Redmond, Washington. Uh
joining me tonight is Venita Loom, our
land development director for America's
West, Lucas Downey and Adonis Trillo,
our Cheyenne community affairs managers,
Randy Reid, our outside council with
Longreer, and Brad Emmens, who you've
met, um principal development
coordinator with AVI, who supports our
entitlement efforts and will be
available to assist in any technical
questions. I appreciate the opportunity
to be with you tonight to present our
request regarding the Highlands
property.
This evening, we are requesting your
recommendation to approve two items. A
reszoning of the Highlands property to
bison or to business park and a future
land use amendment to support that
zoning designation. The Highlands
property is a 3,50 acre parcel just east
of our existing Bison Business Park
campus. We will also be seeking to annex
the property at the appropriate time as
the city process moves forward. These
requests are a critical step in
advancing a strategically planned data
center campus and are intended to work
together to ensure consistency between
land use, zoning, and long-term
planning.
As many of you may have heard, we are
currently in the process of acquiring
this 350 acre parcel and are optimistic
about completing the acquisition over
the summer. Given the early stage of
this effort, Microsoft has not yet
advanced detailed design for the campus.
While we may not have all the answers
today regarding a specific design
element or timing, we remain committed
to being open and transparent with the
community. Just as we have been with our
other local projects,
we believe the requested approvals are
consistent with the city's long-term
growth vision and land use planning
objectives. This will allow us to move
forward in a coordinated way with
infrastructure, utilities, and
development standards under city
jurisdiction. Together, the proposed
bison business or the proposed business
park zoning, the future land use
amendment, and the eventual annexation
into the city provide a co cohesive
framework to guide development of the
site in a way that aligns with the
city's planning goals.
The Highlands property represents an
important opportunity to support
regional economic growth while aligning
with Cheyenne's plan development
patterns. Our intent is to develop a
modern data center campus that aligns
with the future land use plan,
integrates the planned infrastructure
investments, and supports long-term
economic development for the region.
While today's request focuses on these
entitlement actions, we recognize this
is just the first step in a broader
multi-phase process that will include
detailed engineering and additional
opportunities for public review and
input.
We want to emphasize that Microsoft
approaches projects like this with a
long-term commitment to the communities
where we operate. We have been an active
part of the Cheyenne community since
2012. And since 2018, Microsoft has
supported 56 community initiatives
across 28 local organizations with a
focus on education, workforce
development, and community services,
contributing a total of 4.7 million to
local organizations and nonprofits.
As we move forward, we are committed to
paying our way for infrastructure,
minimizing water use, and utilizing
efficient design, contributing to the
local tax base, creating workforce
opportunities, and maintaining ongoing
community engagement.
We understand projects like this of this
scale raise important questions. We have
been proactive in engaging with the
community ahead of tonight's meeting.
This has included a focused neighborhood
meeting with adjacent and nearby land
owners on May 27th for the Highlands
properties specifically as well as a
community openhouse to provide
information and gather feedback on our
expansion efforts on May 28th. That
outreach will continue through a series
of meetings planned for this summer. As
we move into the ne next phases of the
project, we are actively listening to
the community and stakeholders on
infrastructure, water use,
compatibility, and overall growth
considerations. While detailed design is
still to come, these topics will
continue to be addressed through the
city's formal review processes as the
project advances.
These requests are foundational because
they enable alignment with city planning
and development standards, ensure
infrastructure can be planned
holistically, and provide a clear and
predictable path for future entitlements
and public input. In closing, we believe
this resoning and future land use
amendment represent an extension of the
city's growth, an opportunity to
strengthen the local economy, and a
project that can be delivered
responsibly in partnership with the
community. Thank you for your time and
consideration. We're happy to answer any
questions.
>> Okay. Thank you,
Brad. Mr. Chairman Brad Emmens again u
AVI just uh wanted to follow up with a
couple things on um the choices uh of
the BP zone. And if you look in the
applicability section of the BP zone, it
specifically talks about areas like this
as being applicable areas for the BP
zoning. Um and therefore that's why
that's been chosen by the the owner and
the applicant in this situation. Um it
is also adjacent to BP zoning and the
bison business park. Um so it is already
adjacent to a sim the exact same zone.
Um as we move forward if a little bit of
following through this the applicants
the owners did annex actually additional
land. Um so when you see the annexation
it is actually a larger parcel that
they're keeping. Um so there are some
areas that they're uh keeping in the
annexation area compared to the zone
change area. um as well as they are um
and most of that is that ridge line. You
can see that ridge line that kind of uh
cuts diagonally across that. The the the
owner has kept that area even though
they're annexing it at this time. So be
happy to answer any questions of the
commission.
>> You read my mind. Would you clarify
that? I was pulling up the ridge line
discussion from plan Cheyenne in 2014.
>> Mr. chair three. If you if you kind of
look, I guess if you start in the left
just north of the existing campus, you
can see the ridge where the purple and
the gray are. And as that cuts across
there, they've that's why those areas to
the north and east of that area are not
within the zone change because the
applicant is keeping those areas uh to
make sure that conserve the ridge line.
Okay. Thank you. That answers question
number one.
Question number two,
um
how much of this is
servable by the existing
uh water treatment plant, wastewater
treatment plant.
>> Mr. Chairman through so I would let BOP
speak more directly, but there has been
initial discussions that there's
capacity to serve the site. Um there
will be a lift station needed to get the
sewer from the um this parcel back to
the sewer line in Loving Trail. Um but
both those things have the initial
discussions with BOPU uh have occurred
on both of those and at this time they
have capacity for both.
>> But more to my point this is an area
that can be served by that with a with a
lift station.
>> Mr. Mr. Chairman through you again I
would we we have to get clearance from
the board of public utilities prior to
submitting the annexation. Um but they
are also here still I think that
>> you get specifically from them.
Um, I I do note with the with the map
you've got there, just with the shape
and and and the zoning, it it does
appear that a portion of what we're
talking about reszoning here does lie to
the northwest
of that ridge line just by keeping
things angular. I understand what the
the owners are trying to doing, but it
looks like there's still going to be
some that that does lie within this just
by the shape of the polygon.
>> Well, Mr. Chairman, do you again those
polygons are put on by GIS and so I
don't know that they're as accurate as
and then they're overlaid on a photo. So
those um are not
survey level
documents. Um, so
>> thank you. Any other questions of the
applicant by the commission at this
stage? I'm sure we'll have some down the
road.
Okay. Will staff please present your
report
and members of the commission Conway
Planning and Development Department.
So before you you have a future land use
map and a zone zoning map amendment uh
request for land located east of South
Gley Highway and south of the Sweetgrass
uh development.
something I'll just clarify um because
it was kind of brought up
with between the annexation feature land
use map and zone change there are three
different acreages
um basically
so with the annexation you have the 3459
acres for annexation
the future land use map amendment is
3,23
and the zoning map amendment I believe
is around 3,50.
Um
so a couple different things here. Um as
the applicant mentioned, there are
parcels that are being annexed um that
are not part of the zone change and they
are not part of the future land use map
amendment. They're being left basically
they'd be left agricultural upon
annexation and left in that designation
and not part of this development.
um can probably point those out on the
map. It'd be this portion
and then it'd be the ridge line up in
here.
With the zone change, you're basically
looking at this area minus this square.
That square is already annexed and it is
already zoned business park.
um that was done
annexation I want to say was a couple
years ago and then zone change was maybe
last year.
So then that leaves the
um the rest of the area for the zone
change uh to BP.
But the reason it's that square is
included in the future land use map is
we didn't actually do a future land use
map back when it originally came before
you for the initial zone change. And the
applicant would like to clean that up
with this as they're already
kind of doing that for the entire area
to mixeduse employment.
So most of the area um is outside the
urban service boundary on the future
land use map and is designated as
agricultural rural. Uh the agricultural
rural designation was pretty much given
to most land that was outside the urban
service boundary. It wasn't something
that back in 2014 uh was really looked
at as being areas that would develop
with residential, commercial, industrial
or anything of that nature at that time.
Um
however um as you can see with an
application before you uh the market and
property owners noted that this is a uh
prime location uh to basically expand
and allow for development.
Uh the development
of this area would warrant the extension
of the urban service boundary. And I'm
sure BOP can kind of comment on
serviceability,
but should services be able to be
brought into this area, it should be
within the urban service boundary
because it's now a serviceable area.
Um, so that does require also with the
future land use map amendment uh the
expansion of the urban service boundary
as well.
With expanding the urban service
boundary, it does allow for further
development of the South Cheyenne area
and that does in plan Cheyenne further
several economic development goals
contained within plan Cheyenne.
I should note that a portion of the
urban residential future land use
designation is part of this future land
use map amendment.
Uh that portion
is up here in the corner which if you
notice that is part of the Sweetgrass
subdivision
in the Sweetgrass PUD. Um that area was
never proposed for any residential
development. Uh it's on the other side
of the ridge line. Basically they were
just it's part of the PUD but it was
basically labeled as not having
development.
So it does make sense that with this if
they are going to use that property it
should be uh reszoned and also have the
future land use designation changed from
urban residential to mixeduse
employment.
Uh the subject property is located in an
area that's largely undeveloped. Uh
there is the industrial that is to the
west. There is a single kind of smaller
residential subdivision to the
souththeastish
and then you do have the sweetgrass
subdivision that's further to the north
uh northwest um that hasn't fully
expanded throughout the entire uh
sweetgrass pud area.
On the future land use map there is
industrial to the west agricultural
rural to the south and east and then
urban residential to the north. The
agricultural rule would not allow uh for
commercial industrial type uses.
Uh due to its isolated nature, the
subject property is suitable for
industrial development. Noting the
impacts of the industrial development
will be minimal on the large vacant
surrounding properties and the proposed
amendment is consistent with the goals
and policies within plan Cheyenne
with the transportation network. Um,
again, because this wasn't part of the
urban uh service boundary, there isn't
really a transportation network for this
area that would be developed over time
as the property develops. It would
connect into Bison Business Park and
then there could be the potential of
future connections further to the
northwest.
Um, as the property develops, it would
have subsequent applications that would
most likely come before this body in the
forms of platting actions for
dedications of rights of way or platting
of lots.
The
um kind of closest water that we'd be
looking at is going to be over in Bison
Business Park. That would have to be
extended. Same thing with sewer. That is
where your utilities are. it would be uh
need to be extended out to this area.
Um
again, a majority of this land is
proposed uh to be annexed.
And then moving on from the future land
use map amendment
um with the zoning map amendment as I
stated it does not cover the entire area
being annexed. Um it's just a portion of
the land that is proposed for the
development.
Um
again this area consists of roughly 334
acres for the proposed zoning map
amendment.
The zoning map amendment is to the
business park zone district.
The business park zone district does
exist to the west in Bison business
park.
Um the PUD to the north is a for the
most part residential PUD. It does have
commercial aspects. Um does have kind of
some workforce housing provisions and
things of that nature within it. Uh so
for the most part that is a residential
PUB
and then a lot of the other areas
outside city limits uh is LU in the
county. Uh there are oil fields that are
out in this area. I believe further to
the east is a proposed
um
solar array or some sort of solar um
kind of construction going out that
direction more towards the east in the
county.
But for the most part, this area doesn't
have it's mostly vacant. Um, with
kind of little uses here and there. Oh,
there is also a rock quarry that's just
to the northwest along its border.
The BP zone. Um, one thing it does look
at is being kind of on the outskirts of
city limits. So it does look at being on
that edge. Uh same thing with industrial
development. It looks at having kind of
those uses pushed towards the edge of
the community
with the future land use designation to
mixeduse employment. It would support
the reasonzoning to
uh business park.
Uh the other thing with the mixed use
employment zone, I should go back to the
future land use map quickly, is that
that zone district also looks at being
towards the kind of peripheral of um
city limits and on the edge
with the BP zone, you need the 320 acres
um to be allowed to even be incorporated
into the BP zone. Being this is adjacent
to BP zoning and obviously the size of
the area, it would qualify for that zone
district. The BP zone does allow for a
mix of various uses. I do understand
that it's proposed to be data centers.
Um, but looking at BP zone itself, it
does allow for more than just data
centers and more of uh the various uses.
So, should planning commission um
approve or recommend approval of the
future land use designation, then staff
would recommend approval of the business
park zone district. Same thing as our
earlier item. Should the future land use
map amendment uh not have a
recommendation or recommendation of
denial,
then staff would recommend denial of the
zoning map amendment.
With that, I am available for any
questions.
Okay, thank you.
>> Are there any questions for staff from
the commission?
>> I think we're all trying to digest uh
what we shared. Um, I guess when I look
at how you reviewed this and I'm looking
at at number one, uh, beneficial to the
community or addresses issues not
foreseen during the planning process.
But I don't understand the approximate
acreage of Cheyenne's about 20,700.
This this is about 18% of the current
city size, nearly 15th.
How in the world can you even begin to
understand the impact it's going to have
on such a small area when you're
when you have something we can't even
fathom the size of this compared to the
city?
It overtakes the city. So I I don't know
how um I don't even know how you foresee
issues with that because that in itself
is an issue. Um because we're talking
business park, 320 acres, something
almost 11 times the size of that. Wow. I
I can't even imagine. Um so I just want
to know how we we came to the conclusion
here, the city staff, that um you didn't
foresee issues and that it was
beneficial to the community because I'm
really failing to understand that.
So back when the future land use map uh
or basically plan shine was adopted in
2014 again they didn't know what areas
would develop and what areas wouldn't um
this was a similar review criteria when
bison business park was proposed uh
which is along south gley highway um
same thing
>> minus the size of bison business park
Heat. Heat.
Bison Business Park. That area is
roughly 892
acres.
Do you have any further questions,
Commissioner Connor? I I think you've
got the floor.
>> Yeah, I do. Um, so when we look at the
size of some of these campuses,
they're not even online yet. So, we
don't know what that looks like in the
environment, in the community, the
sounds that it makes. I saw the power
lines over my grandma's house and I was
like, "Whoa, not living in your house
ever." So, those hum when they're on.
They're not on yet. Um, how do we know
long-term impacts if we don't even have
one going? How can you even determine
that something
the size of the current city is going to
be an appropriate fit in our community?
Mr. Chair, Director Blue. Mr. Chair,
three to the commission and Commissioner
Connor. Um, we're responding to an
applicant's request for an industrial
zone or a business park zone district
that this location. Any details on their
proposed uh development would need to be
answered directly by them. Um, I do
understand this is large. They have a
lot of land, you know, that they're
working with there. So maybe they could
shed some light on some information as
to why they're choosing that larger land
area. Um but from the long range
planning standpoint, we do have a
variety of land uses that are shown as
mixed use employment and light
industrial in the community. A majority
of the area that is shown as this
industrial category is occupied by our
Union Pacific and Burlington Northern
Rail lines. So it may seem artificially
inflated because those lands are under
railroad control. Um and then there
really are only small pieces that are
available excluding a couple of existing
industrial parks like Swan Ranch. There
are several pieces of land there um
owned by one person. We have some in the
Cheyenne business parkway industrial
park as well. Um so this is again um
looking to add to what is perceived as a
need at this time for um this type of
development um style. anything really
regarding the uh questions regarding how
or why they're looking at this large
area and what their intent would be. I
would just defer that to the applicant.
>> I have another question for you,
Director Bloom, related to the planning
of this and the long-term management of
of things like this. These data centers
are everywhere. If one of them's
polluting the aquifer, polluting the
air, making sound noise, how do you even
begin to determine which one it is to
even properly try to address any of
those issues?
>> Director, Mr. Chair, through you to
Commissioner Connor. That's a great
question. Um, one of the safeguards here
is that this would be a development that
would be located within the city limits.
So, it would be required to connect to
city water and sewer. Um there are other
data centers that could be constructed
in any other part of the country that
are in the unincorporated county or in
other communities where they don't
mandate those connections to to
utilities which could um increase the
risk of discharge. Um, I'm not saying
that the discharge is necessarily
hazardous or known to be hazardous, but
in in our case, um, and Board of Public
Utilities is here. I believe Frank is
Yeah, he is still here, so he'll correct
me if I'm wrong, but any um thing that
is introduced into our system is um
monitored and it has to go through a
check with them to make sure it's
capable. But the um idea that these
would be uh having a direct impact to
our aquifer like for injections or or
those type of things. Um that is
unex that would be unexpected.
>> I think Sharon Noble thought the same
thing. My next question is we talk about
water usage. We can monitor that they're
using water in these systems obviously,
but power requires an incredible amount
of water to generate. And so these
places are consuming power. And so the
water we're using to generate that
power, that's not in this equation. It's
been left out. And
I've lived here my whole life. It's it's
always it's always drought, drought,
drought, drought. That's what we hear.
We see fires in the summers.
I I don't know where the water's coming
from. It's never been here, so I don't
know
where that is.
>> Uh, Director Bloom, and I I think we're
going to want to have BOPU come here
pretty soon.
>> Yes, Mr. chair. I I think uh Bou could
do a really good job um discussing that
um and discussing the uh water needs for
different types of power sources and how
those are are navigating, you know, our
our community and how they are being
introduced into this type of data center
environment.
Commissioner Connor, would you like BOPU
to address some of the water questions?
>> And
please come forward.
>> Uh through you, Mr. Chair. Um when you
talk about the data center wattage usage
itself, it's very low now. They've gone
to closed loop. Um sorry if I'm not
close enough. As for power generation,
that is a big unknown right now. Um
there are newer technologies that use
less water. Um, some are building um,
fuel cells or other alternative power
sources, so to speak, behind the meter
to meet their power needs, but we
currently do don't have any knowledge on
what the next big power supply is and
what the water where the water's going
to come from, unfortunately.
>> Commissioner Connor, do you have more
questions? Well, yeah. And and this
might direct it at Microsoft, but when
we're looking at something this size,
how can we even fathom their energy
needs?
Um to to even tie it back to water, to
even tie it back what's here in our
resources. I I'm I'm at a loss.
>> Okay. Uh we'll we'll hold off before
calling uh before calling Microsoft. Uh,
while we've got BOPU here, may I
um I I alluded earlier to tying into
water and sewer and whether or not this
could be served by the existing water
treatment plant.
Where I'm heading with that is
we're talking about uh first of all, do
I correctly understand that this area
can be served by the water treatment
plant with the installation of lift?
Um, Mr. Chair, let's talk about the two
aspects. On the water side, um, it can
be served. It actually has to be served
by three different pressure zones. So,
we're not quite sure how that's all
going to work yet, but we we've met with
the Microsoft and their engineer and
have made them aware of that and are
working towards a solution on that. Um,
so with the water treatment plant, we do
have capacity if they stay as closed
loop. You know, right now we're looking
at each of the big buildings is probably
going to use the same about as five
homes. So, it's not a huge jump up in
our water usage. On the sewer side, yes,
our wastewater treatment plants have
capacity to handle it because it's just
domestic waste water at this point.
We're also putting in safeguards to
protect that facility. So, one example
is if they're using glycol, they
actually have to build a different
collection system that goes to a storage
tank. I suppose being directly connected
to the sanitary sewer system. So if
there is a leak of glycol or whatever
may ha whatever additives they have in
these closed loop it just doesn't hit
our wastewater treatment plant and cause
issues.
Um and yes potentially there need for a
lift station to service this area. We
just haven't figured it all out. Depends
on what kind of grading they do. In case
you haven't noticed, most of these data
centers do a lot of grading that change
the train dramatically. So, we really
need a plan for whatever they're going
to build before I can tell you for sure
if they're going to need a lift station.
>> Okay. Well, I'll tell you where I'm
headed with this. I've I've never been
completely happy or comfortable or
satisfied with the removal of so much of
the sewerable area
for our existing facilities. And when we
converted,
we went through this future land use
amendment uh process
converting residential to data center
for project Cosmo.
Um I know this area was not projected
for future housing. I remember the 2014
plan adoption process and
this was unforeseen because we nobody
was talking about developing on the
other side of this ridge line.
But as we suffer a
desperate need for more housing in the
community and and and trying to figure
out where is it going to go, is it fair
to say that this with lift station or
whatever could be served with our
existing facilities and is that still
the desire of BOPU to have our future h
urban level housing or our future
housing be within the area serviceable
by the existing water treatment plant
wastewater water treatment plant.
>> Um, Mr. Chair, yes, we want to be able
to service residential area, but as you
said, this was never on our radar. This
was outside of our master plan out of
out of all the master planning
documents. No one expected to go up on
the other side of the ridge. To say this
was, you know, earmarked for residential
in the future is probably not a fair
statement. Could it become residential?
Yes. But keep in mind that there's going
to be significant infrastructure needed
to get to this location that I don't
know if residential development could
support.
Okay.
Did that answer your question
a little bit? Where's the water going to
come from for this? You said that you
said you know each building's the
equivalent of five houses.
Okay. How many built
to translate. We're talking acres. I'm a
old farm boy. When I hear 3,200 acres,
I'm thinking five square miles. I'm
thinking five sections. How many
buildings are going to go in these five
sections? Now, how much water does that
translate to
in Cheyenne?
They can't give me a rough number. Let's
just say there's 40 buildings, shall we?
because that gives me an easy number to
calculate
if I get my calculator. What's that?
Yeah. So, that's 200
that's 50 acre feet of water.
To give you a frame of reference, right
now the BOPU has a firm yield, let's put
Colorado to the side right now, of
22,000 acre feet. In the past couple
years, we've sold anywhere from 11,000
to 14,000 acre feet. So that says we
have 8,000 acre feet and available to us
to sell to customers. So yes, the water
would come from our existing resources
from the Colorado River, a Robroy
reservoir.
>> Glad you mentioned Colorado River
contain curtailment. How can we set that
aside as we're thinking about water use
in Cheyenne?
>> Mr. Chair, I have a question.
Um, hold on. I I I asked a main
question, but and then I'll let you
>> I'm kind Well, I'm I'm kind of on the
same wavelength with you. I was thinking
the same question. I just want to know
gallons. I You're giving me acorage, but
I want to understand what the like the
gallons we're using a day from the data
center. I mean, he compared it to five
homes. How much I mean, five that's I
mean, how many in a household? What is
that? How many gallons is a household?
>> 10,000.
>> Do you want me to answer your question
first, sir, or do you want me to answer
her,
>> please?
>> Mr. Chair, I do want to note that Betsy
Hail, the CEO of Leeds, has also noted
that she can provide some input if
called upon regarding water usage.
>> Okay, we would like that. But I think
let's start with let's start with my
question, then we'll move to
Commissioner Hernandez's.
>> Okay. Uh, Colorado curtailment. Yes,
there's a possibility that the city of
Cheyenne could lose some of its water
rights to a Colorado curtailment. It's
not a permanent water loss, but it could
be for year or two depending on what
happens in the Colorado River.
Currently, with our reservoirs we have
and our demand, we we have about four
years worth of storage that we could
survive on during a Colorado
curtailment. Additionally, we have
possibility to secure alternative water
rights. Those would be water rights
either in the Colorado River or
potentially in the North Plat River that
will allow us to continue to collect
water at Rob Roy and continue to meet
the demand of the city. So, uh, Mr.
Brooks, our director, and myself have
been working diligently on alternative
water rights, but adding another 50 acre
feet would not change the numbers
between four years and 3.99 if I had to
do the calculations. It's it's a very
incremental increase in demand. So we
can facilitate growth at this time. We
have adequate storage for a multi-year
curtailment and that's why I kind of put
it to the side. That is a problem that
is out there and it really is dependent
on mother nature but we don't run out of
water in one year.
>> Okay. Thank you. And can you address
commissioner Hernandez's question? Yes,
please. I believe the question was
through you sir the average household
usage is you know somewhere around
80,000 gallons a year where uh got redo
the math there.
I love it when technology just fails
you.
Uh what did I say?
Oops.
What's that?
Yeah, that's an irrigation number. Yes.
Sorry, my calculator did not cooperate.
So, those 40 data centers I was talking
about, the the 50 acre foot, that's
about
Oh jeez.
16 million gallons where right now we
have a so to speak a surplus I think is
the number of 27 trillion or 2.7
trillion gallons. So it's it's a very
small drop in the bucket of what we
have.
Follow-up question. With this volume of
water use, will we be approaching the
water use levels that we were at
when Holly Frontier was still refining
petroleum?
>> Uh through you, sir? No. Uh Holly
Frontier was using around 2 million
gallons of water a day. Now they're
around 3 to 400,000. So that is still a
we're still at a net loss when Holly
Frontier even with all the data centers
we have. Uh the data centers aren't
consuming that much water. They have to
cool 30 or 40 days a year. So they you
know when they were the evaporative
cooling they would hit us hard in the
summer and then they wouldn't have to do
anything. So we are still as at an
entity still at a net loss from the loss
of Holly Frontier in 2020.
Okay,
can I continue that topic?
>> Yes. Yes, Commissioner Con.
>> Um, when was your fouryear storage last
updated? When were those numbers run?
>> We just ran it last or this year at our
water summit? We had a poll presentation
on it.
>> Okay. And did you um include in any
estimates the the really big data
centers that aren't online yet? because
they haven't started drawing power,
massive amounts of power yet for the
computing that they have. And so I'm
wondering if that type of water is
factored into your projections.
>> So tidbit of information, we've we've
been digging into this. All the data
centers we have that are online right
now used about 93 million gallons last
year. Um which is around a little over
2% of our water sales. So we did do some
calculations on um the possibility of a
big customer coming in and you know we
we we lost you know half a year that we
you went from four to like three and a
half years but we did not do an analysis
of the remaining data centers because
they're actually a very small percentage
of our water usage. No, I understand the
data center centers themselves, but they
use power to generate power. We use
water and so there's I I think there's a
missed variable down the line whether
it's in Cheyenne and it may not be Boo
specifically. I I understand that. Um
but I we're all interconnected in
Wyoming, all the waterways are and so it
it's on the road somewhere.
>> Um Mr. Chair, through you. Yes, there
there is going to need to be more power
generation whether it's nuclear
uh gas turbines whatever the case may
be. I can't speculate on the water usage
and currently no one is trying to
develop a power plant in you know has
moved forward on the power plant
development here in the B the city of
Cheyenne that will be purchasing water
from the BOPU.
May I ask a question follow up with
the the Black Hills energy power plant
that's gas-fed that was built here
recently?
Yeah. Do I
>> Yeah. Yeah. It's been a few years.
>> What kind But what kind of water usage
does it generate and what kind of power
does it do? Do we know if that can be
scaled to what we're talking about here?
Is is it a good place to start
calculating?
>> Uh through you, Mr. Trur. I don't know
those numbers off the top of my head. I
could get those for you. Uh it they're
just not on our top 10 of large
customers. We don't monitor them
heavily.
>> Okay, that's helpful.
Uh any other questions of of BOPU from
the commission at this point? Any
other questions of other city staff?
Because I think we're still on staff
presentation.
Commission,
>> I wanted to get a little more
explanation, pursue this uh part of the
land use plan having to do with this
natural and cultural resources area
that's along that ridge. And
then the report, the staff report says
that
um the development at this location
warrants an extension of the urban
services boundary and an amendment to
the natural and cultural resources area
contained in the plan. However, when I
look at the well, it's not the exhibit
you have on your sheet, but the the AVI
exhibit there at the end of the report,
it doesn't show any difference in that
cross-hatch area. that is that uh
resource area that's along those bluffs.
So I guess I'm wondering is it going to
be impacted or is it going to be
preserved as this development occurs?
>> Mr. Mr. Chair through you. Um so
basically the the original landing that
is there will still be protected um with
this development even that's why as was
noted by the applicant and as I noted
um
the current land owners are annexing a
lot of the ridge line but they're not
selling it. They are keeping the ridge
line because they are keeping that as a
natural cultural resource area and not
developing
um right up onto the ridge line. So
they're keeping that and that is still
protected with even this amendment.
Mr. Chair, through you do you know
specifically what's the I guess natural
and cultural resources? I'm not quite
sure what that all means. The cultural
is there some kind of u Native American
cultural sites? Is that what we're
talking about or what?
>> Mr. Chair, through you that is words
that they used in plan Cheyenne when
they designate any area that they felt
was a cultural natural resource area
just any kind of mixed it all in as one.
So anytime we do the future land use map
amendment and if we have to extend the
urban service boundary we also kind of
extend that with it um to the area. I
think even with the current um
kind of natural resource area
and the way that the ridge line is this
extension actually I think provides more
to it. Um because when they drew the
line they just kind of drew it across
the ridge line. Now this would be
extending it further adding more of that
ridge line into it. Um, I don't know of
any kind of cultural resources out
there. Again, it just goes back to how
the UDC defines
that portion of plan Cheyenne. It calls
it a cultural resource or natural
cultural resource area in plan Cheyenne.
So, that's what we kind of define it as
or call it throughout the staff report
and when we do these amendments.
>> And Mr. Mr. Chair, I'd like to add that
in the director Charles Bloom, planning
development director. I'd like to add
that in plan Cheyenne, this just
identifies, and this is in policy 5.3.CL
plan Cheyenne. It identifies that these
are natural areas that could warrant um
additional mechanisms for preservation.
Those can be things that can be
developed in our unified development
code such as uh slope development
regulations, you know, required open
space dedications, um those type of
items. Um in the sweetg grass PD, which
is adjacent to it and identified this as
um a a natural and open and cultural
area and have proposed that this be a
portion of open space. Um so as they
would move forward with development uh
we would look um to provide some
elements of preservation for the slope
and that is what I imagine is what was
envisioned as the area needing
protection um as this area develops.
followup and this is maybe based on my
foggy recollection, but I seem to
remember
discussion of viewshed of that ridge
line and kind of what that would look
like at least from the city as being
a part of that discussion of preserving
that.
Um, and I guess this is maybe talking
about the the zoning
or what is getting sold in the zoning
maybe more than the the zoning map
amendment or future land use map
amendment. Do we have any concept of
whether any kind of construction
would need to be set far enough back
from that ridge line with the zoning
we're talking about
so that we wouldn't have bunch of roof
lines up above the ridge
uh from the bulk of the viewable from
the bulk of the city or do we have any
idea what kind of
distance between the ridge and the edge
of what's going to be our what would be
our business park zone area that would
facilitate development.
Mr. Chair, three to the commission. Um
no, we we don't have any regulations
that mandate setbacks. um as part of a
development in a subdivision, there
would be a requirement for open space
and we would work with the applicant to
identify open space lands or open space
cont contributions and I'm sure this
would be part of the conversation. But
again, with the comprehensive plan, it
was a policy statement to guide uh the
regulatory framework to start to make
protections of that. Um page uh 108 of
the build Cheyenne the community
character chapter. Um that one actually
talks a little bit more directly about
the natural cultural resource
conservation overlay which is an idea
that was never rolled in or incorporated
into the unified development code. So it
basically is um one that would you know
provide for uh a transfer of development
rights from one area of the community to
another area of the community.
further questions of staff from from the
commission before we get to public
comment
and and I would anticipate maybe by that
point uh leadeds may want to comment
during the public time since I don't
believe leaded is staff
any but any questions from Zoom
Okay, with that I'll open it up for
public comment. Is there anybody here
from the public that wants to speak to
this
Madrid Harmony Meadows? Um
there is a lot there to cover in three
minutes. Um, I just want to first point
out the hypocrisy of scoffing at the
suggestion that this would be zoned as
anything other than agricultural because
that's how it's always been done
apparently. Um, and then less than one
minute later, we're discussing the true
intent of this land, which is
entirely opposite of agricultural. Um
the 2014 map continues to be referenced
as something worth relying on but then
simultaneously acknowledging that
there's no way the 2014 map for this
type of development that we are
currently seeing. Um either the map is
outdated or it is reliable. It can't be
both. Which is it? Um and with the
mention of the UDC, this actually this
land use um annexation gymnastics that's
happening. Um the developer has actually
failed to meet the mandatory review
criteria. It violates section 2.2.1 2.1
D1 which is comprehensive plan alignment
by using a temporary AG label to slip a
multi-billion dollar industrial comp
complex into the city limits. This
completely completely disregards the
intent for this land at it is as it is
outlined in the future land use map. It
also violates section 2.2.1 D2 and D4
which is sound planning and neighborhood
compatibility. Sound planning dictates
transparency. Masking a massive data
center campus as agricultural land
prevents a true honest evaluation of how
a 3,200
plus acre industrial project will impact
the local resources.
Noise levels, traffic, quality of life
for the neighboring homes because yes,
there are people who live in that area.
It violates the fundamental burden of
proof. Section 2.2.1 2.1 requires the
applicant to pro prove public need and
neighborhood compatibility before maps
are redrawn. The public does not need
another data center and a 200 acre
overlap with the business park is a
terrible excuse to annex over 3,000
additional acres that are not intended
for industrial purposes. According to
the land use map,
um this whole process is a procedural
loophole. rather than meeting the legal
burden. Instead, you are asking the
citizens who live here to prove harm
before it has happened, which is
impossible. Thank you. That's also not
how the law was intended or written.
Are there any other members of the
public
here? Okay, sir, please come forward.
>> Hi, my name is Jim Malcolm. I live about
six miles north from this data center um
Sun Valley
and I
don't know a whole lot about this
specific data center but I've been
studying data centers for about the last
two months as I started to learn about
them in Cheyenne. Um,
my concerns are that research on data
centers shows that it raises the ambient
temperature up to six miles away by an
average of three degrees, sometimes much
more than that. Um, another concern is
the infrasound that's been brought up
previously that has not been studied.
And then I would like you to also
consider the fact that there are 70 data
centers and if you approve them in
peacemail in instead of considering them
as a group, you will not understand the
full impact of the data centers on the
Cheyenne area.
So that's all I have to say. Thank you.
>> Thank you,
Pam.
One of the things that Oh, my name is
Janet Tolman and I live in Indian Hills.
One of the things that has been brought
forth in regard to data centers is is
how much um
how many jobs are, you know, going to be
brought into this community. Well,
you know, I haven't heard how many jobs
were brought in when the first phase of
Microsoft was brought in. Frankly, I
don't know of anybody who works for
Microsoft,
but um that's a concern because then we
will need even more housing,
which would mean we need more
electricity and we need more water and
um
you know, right now we're going through
a serious drought and yes, we do have a
supply of water, but we don't know what
next year is going to bring. you know,
every year we just expect snow and we
expect water and what if that doesn't
happen? Um, this is just a real big
concern that like she said 1/5if of
Cheyenne
is is going to be incorporated and I'm
just assuming that um prices of water
will go up and prices of electricity
will automatically go up too. And so
that's uh one of the concerns that a lot
of people aren't looking at either is
and then once again we're have you know
in my area
I don't know it's probably been 15 years
since our residential area had
um road work done other than this little
slips of tar that keep coming off on our
tires and um I'm just wondering how
this is going to impact even more the
infrastructure that we're lacking the
ability to keep up with.
>> Okay. Thank you. Are there any other
members of the public here to speak? I'm
guessing not looking at the
uh councilman.
>> Mr. Chairman, members of the commission.
Um thank you. My name is Larry Wolf. I'm
the senator on the city council
representing Ward One.
Um,
I've sat through so many data center
meetings in the last couple months that
I could probably answer almost all of
the questions that you might have about
them. And your questions are absolutely
right on target and and incredibly
pertinent. Um,
but I think as as you all think about
and I'm not trying to influence your
vote one way or the other on this
because
um you and we are trapped in this
bizarre uh almost set of uh processes
which aren't of the planning
department's creation in which we
haven't even started talking about the
annexation yet. that has not yet
appeared on the council agenda, but it
will very soon. And yet you're talking
about the zoning of this process. And
you have these very legitimate questions
about um what's going to be there and
what's it going to look like and all of
the questions that we've been facing on
data centers. I got home at 1:00 last
Tuesday after listening to more than 67
witnesses, all with the same kinds of
questions that you had. Mr. Leairard was
uh was there I believe. Um so I don't
know how you make sense of this to do
your job. Um the questions that we're
going to have, Councilman Lelay and I u
and and the rest of the council and the
mayor are going to be addressed to, you
know, why does Microsoft need to annex
3,500 acres of land that they may not
use for 10, 15 years. So that really the
question that you asked Commissioner uh
Connor is how can you even say that this
what's gonna what this is going to be
like and what the impacts are because
it's so far away. So Microsoft's going
to have to answer that question for the
city council. Um there are other all
related questions the annexation
agreement that uh should be considered.
Um, so
you know, you're into hour four already
of this. Um, you could spend easily
another four hours on it. Um, there's
going to be a a community meeting on
Saturday for several hours to talk just
about the same questions that you have.
Um, and so all that is just to say I,
you know, you you probably ought to draw
a box around kind of the things that you
want to do. Uh, and um, and then take
these issues up and because, you know,
you've got the Reed property
right next to consider and that has
actually some of its uh, own.
>> Mr. Chairman, are we allowing public
comment over three minutes? Everyone
else was
>> Oh, I'm sorry. I lost track of the time.
You ran out of time. But thank you for
catching that.
>> Also, thank thank you for all the work
that you guys do and and thanks for the
staff for all of this. These are
incredibly complicated issues. Uh and um
um you have you have a part of that.
>> Thank you.
>> Okay.
Um, any other public comment from
online? I believe you indicated that the
leads was here and I I apologize for for
indulging the councilman.
Give me one second.
Uh, Charles Miller, you can go first.
Can you hear me?
>> Yes. Um, commissioners, um, for the
record, Charles Miller,
um, let's see here. I have, uh, quite a
bit of material. Um, as, uh, Councilman
Wolf was also saying, uh, because I've
been involved in gathering material for
this for a while. So, um, but I suppose,
uh, this is going to be my culmination
for this one. Um, I'm entering the
record to perform a final audit on
items, uh, is it correct? I and J or is
that correct? I and J.
>> That is correct.
>> Uh, the Highlands annexation and
reszoning. First, the scale of
deception. We are debating a 30,000 acre
industrial expansion approximately 18%
of the current total size of the city of
Cheyenne. staff is attempting to
characterize this as a minor incremental
increase in utility demand. However, the
Board of Public Utilities just admitted
that this parcel was never on their
master plan and requires significant new
infrastructure, including a dedicated
lift station, to even function. You
cannot reconcile the reality of a 3,000
acre industrial footprint with the claim
that it will have a minimal impact on
Cheyenne's utility or water future.
Second, the ghost project review. The
applicant has formally admitted on the
record that they have not yet advanced
detailed design for the campus. You are
being asked to authorize a massive
zoning change for a project that does
not exist on paper. You have no site
plan, no traffic mitigation, and no
final finalized utility plan. To
recommend approval of a ghost project of
this magnitude is a total abdication of
this commission's fiduciary duty to plan
Cheyenne. Third, the regulatory bypass.
It has been placed on the record that
this business park zoning BP zoning is
specifically sought to navigate around
the Wyoming industrial sitting coun
sighting council ISC permitting process.
This state level process is the only
mechanism designed to force developers
to fund and mitigate impacts on schools,
housing and roads. By reasonzoning to
BP, you are knowingly creating
theictional void that strips this
community of its right to statemandated
impact mitigation. Fourth, the
infrasound liability. Director Bloom
admitted on this record the sh that the
city currently lacks the forensic data
to evaluate or regulate lowfrequency
infrasound impacts from these
facilities. You are being asked to
recommend a massive industrial expansion
for a project known to generate these
impacts while the city openly admits it
is still investigating the hazard. Fifth
cardographic inaccuracy. The applicant's
agent admitted on the record that their
boundary maps are not survey level and
may incorrectly include protected ridge
lines. You cannot base a 3,000 acre
reszoning decision on an inaccurate
maps. The evidentiary burden has failed.
The project is legally,
infrastructure-wise, cardioraphically,
and environmentally premature. I urge
this commission to fulfill its statutory
duty. Recommend denial of the future
land use map amendment and the zoning
change.
>> Thank you, sir.
Is there anybody else that wishes to
speak on this?
Anybody else online?
Oh, leads. Uh, go ahead. And you're able
to unmute yourself.
>> Um, let's just hope I can.
>> You are.
>> Yep. We I can
>> you hear me now?
>> Yes. Yes, we can.
>> Good evening, Mr. chair and uh planning
commissioners. Uh thank you for taking
the time to um have everyone on either
side of this opportunity to discuss
this. Um I want to specifically address
some of the concerns that have been
expressed about transparency and land
use and water and power.
And what we need to begin to understand
is you have a city council, you have
planning commissioners that have been
thoughtful about this for 14 years. Um
that's why these projects are in
business parks because we have
conditions, covenants, and restrictions.
If we put them in business parks, they
are on the board of public utilities.
Water and sewer are regulated and
studied and followed.
um land use regulations apply uh because
we have conditions, covenants and
restrictions. So um and we also have
Black Hills Energy with a three-year uh
study of transmission and ability to
provide power through their large load
tariff. So while I would like to um
call out this 3,200 acres or any growth
of any industrial use or light use
manufacturing
um to be under a um blanket of
suspicion. Um, I need to assure all of
you that are listening that for 14
years, we have done everything we can to
protect the citizens of Cheyenne, the
residents of Cheyenne, the rateayers of
Cheyenne, the water resources, the sewer
capabilities. And I think we should
actually celebrate the fact that in
Cheyenne, Wyoming and Laramie County,
we've kind of done it right. And I
actually have appreciated the last
several weeks of debate because from Ms.
Madrid and Ms. McAdams. We have learned
a lot about what communities want, our
citizens need, whether it's Walters or
whether it's um Highway 85. And so I
look forward to further conversations,
but I want to assure the planning
commissioner, Mr. chair through you to
Miss Connor that um OPU and your
planning department, your engineering
department, they're listening and
they're hearing and your city council
and your planning commission are as well
and Cheyenne Leadeds is as well. So, we
want to hear more. We want to ensure
that what our community needs are being
met.
>> Fine.
Or okay. Thank you. Is there anybody
else that from the public that wants to
speak on this?
Anybody else on Zoom?
Okay. With that public comment going
once, going twice. Public comment is
closed
and for members of the public or people
that are wonder what's where we're at
and and we'll ask the the applicant to
speak and and and and the city. Uh just
as a reminder um
the first question we have to ask is
whether to actually amend the future
land use map from agriculture to
what mixeduse employment.
um
talking about the the changes that would
need to occur to the 2014 map
uh in order to permit um move moving
forward
with a business park zoning for the
proposed uses. So that's that is the
question that is before us is trying to
wrestle with with whether that change is
appropriate. And then secondly,
the question that we're discussing is is
whether to
if we approve that, would we then
recommend a reszoning away from the
default agricultural zoning that we
discussed earlier to a business park
zoning? Um, with that would
would the applicants please come forward
and address some of the questions that
have been raised during public comment.
>> Mr. chair through you Braden Savvi you
have specific questions that you've got
listed
>> um
not specific uh beyond we I I know we
asked about footprint I I know we asked
about uh water consumption and that we
asked about uh power demands
and and we had some discussion about
just sight lines and and cultural issues
in the area that that your client is
proposing to to purchase and develop.
>> So, Mr. Chair, through you uh the stuff
that I can speak to uh it was with
working with the current owner and their
design of what they were willing to sell
and that was all based upon keeping the
current ridge line and sight views. um
is why the shape of that boundary on the
northwest side um has
the design that it does. Um
um I you know for the the questions on I
think Frank answered most of the
questions on the water consumption again
when you're when you're working in
development you have to go in steps and
the first step is to make sure that the
the land is zoned current for you to to
move forward. um you know they're your
de the developer um they they have to
spend million I don't I guess I don't
even know how much money they spend but
they spend money for us to provide all
the this the things for this process and
then once they have their zoning they go
through the site plan process through
the site plan process that that's when
they get with the board of public
utilities for the extensions of
utilities the extensions of road
infrastructure and all of those things
on the city side um they are required to
submit a energy power plan to Black
Hills. Uh that gets reviewed by Black
Hills. Black Hills decides if they can
serve the project. Um and then what
improvements that are required to serve
the project. Then the developer is
required to build those that
infrastructure. Um I believe it was
brought up by Cheyenne Leads that
there's a tariff uh system for power and
that these large users are in a
different pool is the way I understand
it. Again, I think I would prefer Black
Hills to actually
answer the question, but there's like a
pool, the residential pools here, the
large user pools here, and that and that
these large data centers cannot make any
effects onto the to the residential pool
of electricity. Um,
so I think that's the ridge line and
Frank's stuff on the water and then what
I know on the on the power side, but
>> and were there any other questions that
uh commission had that came out of
public comment or that need to bring up
with the
>> There was one that a public comment had.
They did ask um how many employees
this area planned to and I have another
question up there. We answer that one.
>> Chairman D. I do not know the amount of
employees that they have brought in, but
I will see if any of the current people
do.
>> And I think they were in reference to
longterm employees, permanent.
>> Correct. Yeah.
>> And and hold on before we get there. Did
you have a question for Mr. Emmens? Oh,
for Microsoft. Okay,
>> Mr. Chair, through you. Uh, for longtime
term employment, our data centers employ
roughly 50 operational technicians
per data center.
>> Would you say per data center? Is that
per building?
>> Yes, sir.
>> Okay.
>> And Commissioner Connor, you had a
follow-up question as well.
>> Uh, my last my last question. I mean
that's really not that many employees
when we look at it especially for the
size this is coming to when we don't
know how many buildings are going to be
there. What happens when this technology
is obsolete?
I'm sorry I don't have an answer for
that question.
I just think that's something we have to
consider because that's not been
something that's brought up long term.
We're saying this is cutting edge.
It's changing constantly. It's changing
fast. And I see the day when this is
very much obsolete technology because
we're building quantum computers.
>> Ma'am, while you're here, um couple of
the things that were alluded to
um during the discussion.
one,
we were throwing out the term worthy
buildings. And
is there any projection on actual
projection, not just random numbers for
calculation convenience that we're
talking about in terms of projected
footprint, projected buildings, and why
five square miles?
>> Mr. Chair, through you. Um, at this
time, we don't have um a specific number
of buildings. We do not own the land
yet. So the the amount of due diligence
that we've done is just to see if the
land is developable. Once we acquire the
land and we move into the next phase of
our development, um meaning detailed
design, at that point we would evaluate
how many buildings are able to be
developed on this land. Um as for your
second question, why why five square
miles or why 3,000 acres? Um our
commitment to the community is long-term
investment and this is one way which we
do. So all of these acres will not be
developed at one time. This is something
that's going to be over a long phase
development and will continue over the
course of 15 20 plus years.
>> Okay. Thank you. Um, can we even talk
about rough ranges of buildings? Because
I I believe you mentioned 50 permanent
jobs per building, data center building.
You know, is 40 actually a pretty good
number to to think about? Is it are we
think are we talking about expansion
that's less than that more than that you
know within your ability to to say what
are we actually planning for here as
we're talking about amending our maps
and thinking about the zoning and and
everything else that we have to think
about communitywide long-term in
response to
I I like the term 16%
growth 16.5% but that's my numbers
chair through you. Um I don't have an
exact number of buildings or an estimate
at this time. Um that that's outside of
my area. I would have to rely on our
engineering team for that.
>> Okay. I'm not asking for exact.
>> I I don't have a spec I don't have a
number at this time. We're not a campus
of this size anywhere that you could um
draw a parallel from.
>> We do not at this time. We do not have a
campus of this size to pull from.
>> Mr. chair. Uh we do have Betsy. We do
have Betsy Hail with Cheyenne Leadeds
who's been working with the applicant
and the applicant's agent on this
project who has raised her hand. Um
>> like that information please
information. So Betsy will go ahead and
unmute.
uh
Commissioner Wigum and planning
commissioners um Cheyenne Leeds has been
doing economic development for 40 years.
And um for those of you that don't know
the um
building that Magpole occupies was a
Safeco building before it was a Magpole
building. And so when um we look at
economic development and I've been in
this industry for 40 years, uh the best
types of economic development are when
you build buildings in your community.
And when a business leaves your
community and there's still a building,
you have the opportunity to fill that
building. And so while you consider the
opportunity with one of the top five
companies in the world, don't worry
because boots on the ground. That
building is in your community. And
therefore
we have an opportunity to fill that
building with the next opportunity. And
it is exactly what we did when Safeco
left that building and we filled it with
Magpole just as we were doing with the
Arundle building now that Stag Arms has
moved out and we have other um companies
moving in just as we have done out in
Swan Ranch and so much of what we do in
economic development people don't see
and we don't talk about because the best
types of economic development
are when you have land and buildings and
they're in your community. And so
I appreciate
uh Commissioner Connor's question and I
hope someday that we get to have a very
robust conversation around economic
development
because once they put a stake in the
ground,
that building is really ours. It's not
the company that puts the building on
the ground. It's our building. Cuz if
they decide to leave, guess what? The
building's still in our community. Then
we have to fill it. We have to decide
what we do. And so I appreciate the
question. I appreciate the opportunity
to answer it. And thank you so much for
being 40, 50, 100 year forward thinking.
>> Thank you. Um, do we have do we have
Black Hills here? Because there's been
lots of questions about power, power
access, generation, cost, etc. Okay.
Are there any other questions that we
have of the applicants from the
discussion
from the commission?
I think we're ready for a motion.
And again, we're talking about a motion
to amend the future land use plan
from the agricult the agricultural that
that was designated in 2014 to
to something new.
I'm looking for a motion to discuss to
vote on one way or the other.
>> Mr. Chair.
>> Uh, Commissioner Leairard,
>> I move to approve the resolution
amending the future land use plan for
roughly 3,238.8
acres of land east of South Gley Highway
and south of the Sweetgrass development
as shown in the future land use map
provided. adding land to the urban
service boundary and changing the land
from agricultural
and urban residential to mixeduse
employment.
>> Thank you, Commissioner. Do we have a
second so we can cast a vote?
>> I'll second it.
>> Thank you. I've got a second by
Commissioner Mtha. Discussion by the
commission.
Commissioner Carr,
>> just just a comment. Um, you know, I've
heard a lot of testimony um tonight and
and through public comment and through
people who want to see these things
happen, want to see these changes. Um,
I don't think any of those people grew
up here. Um, this is my hometown. This
isn't what I want to see happen to it. I
know there's a lot of people that feel
the same way. And, um,
I just hope that that's taken into
consideration.
Okay. Thank you, Commissioner. Any other
comments, discussion,
proposed amendments?
Anything online?
Hearing none.
Well, staff, please call role. And
again, this in order to advance a
recommendation, we need four vote, four
affirmative votes.
Okay.
Megan Connor,
>> no.
>> Bob Mile,
>> yes.
>> Amy Hernandez,
>> no.
>> Tony Lair,
>> I
Wiggum forces.
>> I,
>> Mr. Chair, due to state statute, even
with the 3 to2
um in favor of the motion, it is still
going to be a recommend basically
recommendation of denial to city
council.
>> Okay. Thank you. And now we need a
motion on item J, which is the zoning
map amendment.
>> And Mr. Chair, just real quick quick
staff report because the motion for the
future land use map did fail. Um staff
does then recommend uh that the planning
commission recommend denial to the
governing body.
>> Okay. Thank you. Do I have a motion?
I move to recommend the governing body
deny the reszoning of approximately
3,34.7
acres of land east of Southley Highway
and south of the Sweetg Grass
development to BP Business Park as shown
in the attached zone change map. Noting
that the project does not meet the
review criteria for approval.
>> Thank you. Do I have a second? Oh, I
seconded by Commissioner Hernandez.
Staff please call roll or I guess any
discussion by the commission before I
call for a vote hearing none. Will staff
please call ro and again this is a
recommendation of denial. So please vote
yes if you're in favor of the motion. Do
not vote no.
>> Bob Matthia
>> no.
>> Tony Larair I.
>> Megan Connor.
>> Yes. Amy Hernandez.
>> I,
>> Mr. Chair, that motion passes.
>> Okay. Thank you.
It's approaching 10:30.
Um,
we've got one more item going. We've got
one more item left. One more, I guess, a
couplet.
Uh again, uh I'd like to address uh
items K and L together or at least uh
receive the the the reports. Uh will
will staff please read items K and L
into the record. Item K, PUDC-26-122.
Read future future land use map
amendment.
Item L is PUDC-26-121
read zoning map amendment.
>> Okay. Will the agent for the applicant
please come forward and tell us what
we've got.
>> Uh chairman planning commission members
Brad Emmens Avi agent for the owner Reed
Land Company LLC. And similar to the
last one, the applicant is Microsoft.
We'll try to we have another little
presentation. So, I'm just turning it
over to Rachel Irwin real quick to do
that part and then we can get back into
a little bit of the information on this
one.
>> Good evening again, chair, members of
the planning commission staff, and
members of the public. My name is Rachel
Erling for the record, land development
and permitting program manager for
Microsoft located at one Microsoft Way,
Redmond, Washington.
I'll keep this item brief as the request
for this reed property is very similar
to the Highlands property we just
discussed. For project Reed, we are
requesting your recommendation to
approve a resoning to business park and
a future land use amendment to support
that designation. The Reed property is
approximately a 385 acre parcel located
off South College Drive and like
Highlands, it represents an early stage
development opportunity to thoughtfully
plan for a future data center
development. These requests are intended
to ensure alignment between zoning,
future land use, and long-term
infrastructure planning under city
jurisdiction consistent with the
framework we just described.
As with Highlands, this project is still
in the early stages of acquisition and
planning. Detailed design has not yet
been developed and there will be
additional opportunities for public
engagement as the review for this
project advances.
Microsoft's approach here remains the
same. Long-term partnership with the
community, responsible infrastructure
planning and investment and ongoing
engagement as more details.
In closing, this request reflects
another step in supporting coordinated
growth that we believe aligns with the
city's planning goals and economic
development objectives. Thank you again
for your time and consideration and
we're happy to answer any questions.
>> Um
before I call for other commissioners, I
would like to know where the housing is
going to go if we displace the our
our future land use map plan for this to
be housing. It's a J. It's nearby
housing. Where's the plan for the
housing to go if we convert all of our
future land use
to business parks.
>> Mr. Chairman, through you Bradmonds,
AVI, please.
>> Um, so speak to specifically to that. I
would say about 20 to 30% of this
project is already mixeduse employment
or activity center locations. Um, so
it's really just an expansion of that.
Um, we have this landowner has had this
property under contract twice by
residential developers. Both times those
developers could not make it work. So
whether it's in the land use amendments
process to be residential or not, it's
it's not it's not been able to be in to
work its way through the process before.
It's been under contract by a a
residential developer that we don't um
offer services to or they didn't use our
services on that one. Um and then we had
an apartment complex developer that
looked at the whole thing and and the
site just not would not work uh for
their development. So, I think there is
there is two parts to it. I I do believe
there we're going to have to find other
residential areas. Uh there's about I
want to say a thousand acres of
sweetgrass left that's undeveloped. Uh
they haven't done another subdivision in
probably three years. Uh there's land uh
Whitney Ranch, there's ranch at Saddle
Ridge, there's land south of Meta that
have all still being um still saved for
residential areas. So, um I do
understand the concern, um as as we move
forward, um there there were there's
definitely going to have to be lands
found for residential, but I can say
that this this land has been looked at a
couple times already for residential and
it and neither time as it moved forward.
So,
any other questions for the applicants
from from the commission?
>> Mr. Chair,
let's go to uh Commissioner Ma first.
Oh, I'm sorry. Um, I have a I guess it'd
be for for Rachel. I didn't know her. I
don't remember her last name. Um, how
critical is it to have the whole 32 or
3,000 acres to carry out the plans that
you're you're you're currently uh
developing? Is it some of this some land
banking that that's going to occur to
asssure you're going to have enough land
in the future to have a coordinated
development over the whole area?
>> Chair through you. Um I do want to make
one distinction before I answer that
question. The 385 acre reed parcel that
we're discussing is not part of that
3,200 acres that we were discussing.
That was the Highlands parcel. Um,
however, to answer your question,
overall, yes, we do plan to land bank to
have an opportunity for a long-term
development and an investment in the
community.
>> Commissioner Mthay, any further
questions?
>> Um, you said that you had a plan of how
many years for that?
>> Chair through you. Um, we're estimating
right now that this is a 1520 plus year
development plan if we include that
3,200 acres. This is not speaking
specifically to the 385 acre reed parcel
that we're we're discussing at the
moment.
>> Okay.
>> Commissioner Lar, did you have a
question?
>> I did. My question has to do with the uh
uh projected roadways
in this parcel uh from the future land
use plan and specifically Fox Farm. It
extends a little to the east and then
south occurs to the south and then
Allison which would extend due east and
then eventually um connect up with an
extension of College Drive. Is that do
you expect that's still going to be
compatible with the development you'll
design on this parcel?
>> Um Mr. Chairman through you to
Commissioner Leard. So the uh we have
done uh modeling with the uh consultant
for the city that um that is used in the
NO and ran uh the numbers for Allison
and Fox Farm. uh what's come out of the
now this is assuming that it's changed
to BP and a data center and in those
situations that Allison Road would carry
very little traffic um because of the
the low um amount of future long-term
employees. Um and so um we have not
finalized Fox Farm. So we've left Fox
Farm still on the on the map as it goes.
Again, it's a placeholder in there. not
exactly probably where we would end up
going, but we didn't want to take it
completely off the map because it hasn't
been fully vetted or on whether that
could be removed or not. But, uh, from
the traffic modeling through the NO
office, Allison Road was, um, uh, able
to be removed if, again, we would not
propose Allison Road to be removed if
the feature land use amendment in the
zone change did not go through. Um,
thank you. Any further questions?
Any other further questions for the
applicant from the commission?
Will staff please present your report?
Mr. Chair, members of the planning
commission, Seth Lloyd with the City of
Shine Planning and Development
Department. The proposal in front of you
is two parts. One is a um future land
use map amendment of roughly 300 acres.
Um, as noted by the applicant, it's not
for the entire acreage as some of this
acreage is already um mixeduse
employment by the future land use plan.
Um, however, the resulting zone change
would be for the entire acreage of about
approximately 385 acres. Um, obviously
these two items are related, so I will
discuss them together. I will start with
a future land use map amendment. Um this
future land use map amendment um also
includes a roads amendment um for um I
think it was commissioner leard that
asked that question. Um so to start off
with the roads um this is what the
applicant had provided to us most
recently. Um the map on the right shows
the extension of Fox Farm without
Allison Road an Allison Road connection.
Um due to the vagaries of process um
that road alignment may change over time
um these master transportation map
roadways are not meant to be the exact
location of the roads. These are general
locations. So depending on exactly how
development occurs um we would expect
Fox Farm to somehow connect from college
to the extension of East West College. I
don't know if we have a name for that
street yet. Um that would eventually
connect further eastward. Um the
original application from the applicant
did not include either Fox Farm or
Allison Road. Um and so in the staff
report we had the condition they include
at least Fox Farm Road. The applicants
resubmitted to include Fox Farm Road. So
staff will recommend um uh without that
condition. Um, the future land use map
for the area currently has a mix of
mixed use employment, mixed-use
commercial, community business, mixeduse
residential, and urban residential. Um,
the future land use map gets a little
prescriptive in this area, kind of
guiding um, development along the
extension of Allison Road. Um, and then
some mixed use commercial to the south.
Um,
it seems unlikely that the property
would develop exactly as shown, but
perhaps a mix of residential and
commercial and industrial uses would be
appropriate. Um,
the
uh question becomes, is it appropriate
to have mixed use employment over the
entirety of the parcel as opposed to
over just a portion of the parcel? the
northern um area is kind of surrounded
by mixed use employment on three sides
and obviously mixed use employment is
meant to um be developed along College
Drive. Um historically uh that that
mixed use employment along College Drive
is roughly 900 ft to 1,000 ft deep off
of College Drive. Um historically most
of our industrial parcels in the
community are about that deep. We don't
have really large parcels um very
frequently. However, with the new data
center development program, a lot of
these data center parcels are looking
for much larger parcels. And so, if we
um assumed every parcel along college
were to be a data center parcel,
extending the depth of this property
would be a more appropriate option. Um,
so depending on if you want to look at
this as
um trying to develop with the most
modern mixeduse employment demands that
the city has, it would be appropriate to
expand the uh mixeduse employment to the
entire property. Um, if we're looking at
retaining uh residential development in
this area, then it wouldn't be as
appropriate to extend a mixeduse
employment. Um, the applicant only
provided a request to amend the land use
map within their boundaries. So, I would
note that this would retain urban
residential to the east of this
property. Um, that would be another
reason to push Fox Farm Road through is
if that area to the east of this
property developed urban res with urban
residential development.
Um,
on the balance, staff recommends
approval of this uh future land use map
amendment. Um, and I'm available for any
questions on that. Um, but I will also
speak to the zoning real fast so we can
cover both items. Um, the zoning is once
again dependent on the future land use
map. Um, large acreages of mixed use
employment is appropriate to zone BP
business park. Um, but the urban
residential designation and the mixeduse
commercial designation are not as
appropriate. Certainly the urban
residential use uh future land use
designation is not appropriate to be BP
and the mixeduse commercial would allow
more industrial than we would expect for
a mixeduse commercial area. Um so the BP
zone would not be appropriate if the
future land use uh map amendment is not
approved. Um should the future land use
map amendment be approved um the large a
large acreage is involved and the future
land use designation of mixuse
employment would make BP appropriate.
Um, I'm available for any questions on
either of these two items.
>> Okay, thank you. Questions for staff
from the commission?
>> I do have a question for staff. Um,
Seth, can you remind us of the sound
limits on the business parks?
>> Um,
Mr. share through you. The sound limit
that triggers uh uh a more intense
zoning or conditional use approval is uh
50 dB at the pro 55 dB at night at the
property line of a residential property.
Um and then there are steps up depending
on if it's an industrial use uh
industrial zone or um if it's daytime.
So the minimum the the lowest
maximum is 55 dB at the property.
And that's during the day.
>> That that would be at night.
>> And what's during the day?
>> I think it's 65 at the property line
during the day.
>> 6, sorry, 60 at a residential property
during the day. Industrial properties
have a higher limit.
>> Um, so a question for you as we look at
it. This border is an agricultural
college that's full. Their pride and joy
is a rodeo team. Um, animals are even
more sensitive than humans. And so when
we're talking about this kind of noise
next to a community college that's the
fabric of our community, how
I don't see how those two things are
compatible.
Any other questions of staff from the
commission?
I have one. Did staff have more
heartburn about uh amending this a
amending the map in this case than in
the last?
>> Mr. Chair, um staff has definitely had
discussions on these various proposals.
Um so
when it comes to a data center locating
inside a business park that a previously
established business park, um staff has
less heartburn over that. when it comes
to agricultural rural areas that we did
not anticipate to develop um that is not
as as as much heartburn as a residential
area. Um this property is a little bit
more concerning because of the um this
one is more likely to have
infrastructure available to be built
than say the southwest drive one that we
had earlier on the agenda. But on the
other hand, this one also already has
mixed use employment over parts of the
parcel. Um, so there is there is
definitely conversations among staff on
the applicability and appropriateness of
these. Um, I think it's pretty clear in
the staff reports on both Southwest
Drive and this item that um there's
uh reasons to both approve and deny
these applications. They're they're not
cut and dried. They're not um as
straightforward as some of the other
applications we get might be.
>> Okay. Okay. And as a followup, is it
fair to say that although the future
land m use map in this situation appears
to be more prescriptive, is it fair to
say that it's at least my interpretation
it is more reflective of anticipating
this being kind of a a natural normal
extension of the urban fabric with some
sort of a mix of commercial and
residential and maybe some job centers.
But is that a fair way to describe what
we're looking at that we're looking at
changing than the last couple? Mr.
Terry, this this particular the way the
future land use map is um
arranged as it is presently does
anticipate a more broad mix of uses,
urban development um uh and even looking
at it as a as a kind of fuzzy line map
as it were, we'd still expect to see
houses, commercial development,
industrial development all on this
parcel as a whole under the current
designation.
And I don't know if if this is for staff
or for for
boooo, but is this is it fair to say
that this parcel is much more easily
served most much more easily served with
both water and sewer than with existing
infrastructure than
than the other examples we've talked
about tonight?
>> Uh through you, Mr. Chair. Yes, there
the existing facilities are there and
they're accessible. There's no major
extensions needed.
>> Okay, thank you. Any other questions of
staff from the commission? I'll open it
up for public comment. Is there anybody
here from the public that wishes to
speak on this item or on either of these
items? Either the uh future land use map
amendment or the proposed zoning.
Sir,
>> Jim Malcolm, uh, chairman, uh, I'm not
exactly sure how to refer to all of you.
Thank Thank you for listening to me
today. I know it's late. My comments,
um, for
>> Ah, but thank you. Okay,
>> turn off the
>> Yeah, it's late tonight, isn't it?
>> I'm sorry. Ah, my comments on this one
are similar to my comments on the last
one. Um, except this one is actually
closer to where I live. It's just a
couple miles from where I live. And um I
I my my day job is in IT. I work with
data centers. I am not against data
centers, but the difference between the
ENCAR facility of 1.5
um megawws of energy versus the
Microsoft data center across the street,
which is like 100 times that versus the
these other these data centers they're
talking about. These data, these newest
data centers that have not been built or
they've been considered being built are
orders of magnitude larger than the data
centers that we have been dealing with
in the past. And to call them data
centers is to think of them in the wrong
way. That is to think of them as like
the these smaller data centers. I worked
in a building with a data center. was on
this it was on this the next floor above
from where I was working and the Emerson
building downtown and there's a data
center there and across the street you
call the AT&T building a data center.
These are small these are
inconsequential compared to what we're
doing now. The amount of heat basically
we're putting space heaters in these
areas. They do the computing stuff but
all the computing ends up generating
heat in the the local areas. the the
levels of impact on our environment and
local areas is needs to be understood
before we make decisions on them. I
ask that we postpone making decisions on
these until we understand them better.
Thank you.
Okay. Thank you. There any other members
of the public who want to speak on
the read items?
Okay.
Um,
who have we got?
>> Charles Miller, you should be able to
unmute yourself.
>> Okay. Thank you, Mr. Miller. And I
remind you we're speaking specifically
on the zoning map amendment and then no
and well the future land use map
amendment for the read parcel and then a
proposed zoning reszoning on the on the
reed parcel.
>> Okay. Um
um Mr. Chair, commissioners for the
record, Charles Miller, Laramie County.
Um, I'm I appeared tonight to perform a
final forensic audit of the Reed land
requests items 121 and 122. Minutes ago,
you exercised your statutory duty to
deny a deeply flawed industrial
expansion. Consistency and governance is
not an option. It is a mandate. To grant
this application would be an arbitrary
and capricious departure from the
findings you just established. I direct
your attention to four fatal violations
that demand a motion for denial. First,
statutory abandonment of the general
welfare. Your own staff report for item
121 makes a stunning legal admission on
page five. It states verbatim that
sacrificing this land would adversely
affect the general welfare of the
community. Due to Cheyenne's documented
housing crisis, um moments ago, the
chair rightly asked where the displaced
housing will go. You cannot legally
reach a positive finding of fact for a
zone change when your own planners have
documented on the record that it
actively harms the public welfare by
eradicating nearly 400 acres of planned
residential and mixeduse neighborhoods.
Second, the land banking confession and
street sabotage. The applicant just
formally admitted on this record that
they are land banking. We have empire
empirical proof of what that means. In
West De Moines, Iowa, Microsoft
purchased massive parcels, halted
construction, and left the city with
empty, non-productive land for a
prolonged period. Yet today, they demand
the immediate removal of two
masterplanned streets, the Allison Road
and Fox Farm Extensions. You're being
asked to amputate the city's
transportation network simply so a
trillion dollar corporation can hoard
vacant land. Third, the anonymous
governance trap. Cheyenne Leeds
previously suggested the public is
protected by private CCNRs. That is a
dangerous legal fiction because Fininsen
abolished beneficial ownership reporting
under the Corporate Transparency Act in
March 2025. The LLC's governing these
business parks operate as fully
anonymous shell companies. If you
approve this BP zone, you are
outsourcing municipal environmental and
noise enforcement to anonymous entities
that the city possesses zero statutory
authority to regulate. Fourth, the
standard of proof failure. This
commission requires a finding of fact
that the development is compatible with
the surrounding area and that that
infrastructure is adequate. You have no
campus plan. You have no utility master
plan. The applicant explicitly admitted
tonight that they do not have a campus
of this size to pull from. There is zero
evidence to support a positive finding
effect. If you approve this after
denying Highlands, you are creating a
record of inconsistent application of
your own review criteria, the very
definition of arbitrary and capricious
decision-making. I urge a mo motion to
deny both the land use amendment and the
reasonzoning. Thank you.
Thank you. Is there anybody else from
the public that wants to speak online?
Who have we got?
>> Betsy, you should be able to unmute
yourself.
>> Good evening, Mr. Chair. Um,
I appreciate the fact that Mr. Miller
and several of your speakers before
uh made the comments that they did. But
I also want you to appreciate the fact
that there are families who own this
land
in Wyoming that have been Wyomingites
for generations over a hundred years.
And they have an opportunity to sell
their land to the people that they'd
like to sell their land to. and that
those buyers have an opportunity and a
right
to develop that land as they see fit
because they are in Wyoming. And I also
appreciate the fact that those
uh wonderful people that are online and
in the room have concerns about the
environment. They have concerns about
water. They have concerns about power.
But one of the things that they can
count on is that in Wyoming, you as
planning commissioners and our city
council and our county commissioners
were protect their rights, all rights.
And so as I look at this decision on the
Reed property, I would hope that um you
as commissioners will look at this as an
opportunity for this family who's been
in this land for over a hundred years to
do what they feel is best with their
property and move forward. And so I
appreciate your consideration
and I appreciate your thoughtfulness
in the fact that we have land use
guidelines, a public utility, we have
Black Hills, everyone has thought about
this and so thank you very much. And uh
it's late. I know we're all tired, but
um I think it's about time that we um
make decisions based on the rules and
regulations and the laws that guide us.
Thank you.
>> Thank you. Do we have anybody else
online?
Okay. Public comment going once, going
twice. Anybody else? Public comment is
closed.
Um,
in keeping what we've done,
will the applicant come uh please come
forward?
I don't know that we've got
any open questions
unless there's one that slips my old
tired mind.
>> Um, Mr. Chair, I didn't write down any
that I thought were missed, but happy to
answer any questions.
>> Any Okay, any any more open issues? You
you you mentioned that that the this
land has been under contract a couple of
times for commercial
and it didn't work at the current price
points and the current interest rates.
Is that correct? Mr. Chairman, through
you I can uh
Dan Reed is here who is the current
owner of the property. They've had it
listed for many years. Um, I do know
that like I said, one residential
developer, they do a little bit of
commercial, but primarily develop
residential, they looked at it, had it
under contract, did due diligence on it
for six to nine months, and then move
forward. And then our developer does
apartments
um and we're going to do apartments on
the west side and residential on the
east side. And the property did not work
out uh for those uses for them either.
So, um I that would be the only
>> Do we know if there was something
topographic or environmental there or is
it just not enough demand for housing in
Cheyenne to justify building houses?
>> Mr. Chair, you there are some things
that make us it's kind of the opposite
of most parcels. It's a little like for
residential, it's almost too flat. Um,
which always sounds funny, I think,
because so many times we're working on
trying to get rid of elevations, but
it's a pretty flat parcel, which makes
it hard for uh storm water detention um
getting pipes to the to those
properties. Um,
so I wouldn't say there was um anything
crazy on the parcel, but again, there's
other land in Cheyenne that was better
suited for residential at the time. And
so those those people move to the to
those properties. So um but I would let
the owner speak. He would know more than
I would.
>> Okay. And and I've got a question that
came up during the discussion. It's been
a a question that's come up several
times and I think this is for Microsoft.
Several commenters have have commented
on on heat generation
and and what it does to the surrounding
area.
Would you please address that for us
before we
since this is right up next to the city
and not up over a ridge
>> chair through you? Um my expertise is
not in um heat or engineering. I would
have to defer to my engineering team.
So, I'd be happy to to get that offline
and provide that to you, but I do not
have any of that information at my
disposal.
>> Thank you. It' probably be nice to have
some of this
close to town. And Mr. Reid,
welcome. As we're talking about you,
you're you're the one that has has the
most direct stake in this as the owner.
Well, I'd like
>> I'd like to think that the city of
Cheyenne has a stake in it as well in
terms of economic development, the
growth of the city, the well-being of
the city, and the tax basis. Uh, but let
me say that we have had this property on
the market for 30 years now in one form
or another. We've listed it with uh real
estate agents. We worked with AVI to
work out a plan to sell it in plots. Uh
which uh one of which uh as Brad said uh
didn't work out. The buyer went through
due diligence, decided to back out,
decided that the because it's flat,
because it's lowlying, the groundwater
was an issue for them. another
developer, uh, a Cheyenne developer,
exactly as Brad said, backed out of the
project after doing his due diligence
because the land was too flat. He didn't
fel feel he could drain it. And um, you
know, since then, the only inquiries
we've had for the property have been uh,
industrial.
>> Okay. Thank you. And just for the
record, I took umbrage at somebody
referring to your cows as being vacant
land,
whoever's cows are out there. But thank
you.
>> Yeah.
>> Any other questions from the commission?
Hearing none,
I'll accept a motion
on the future land use plan amendment.
Okay, Mr. Chair,
>> I'll I'll read the the uh motion.
>> Uh I'm going to re recognize
Commissioner Mthay.
>> Okay. I move to approve the resolution
amending the future land use plan for
lots one and two block one reed land
addition located east of College Drive
south of I80 as shown in exhibit A from
urban residential mixed use residential
mixeduse commercial and community
business to mixeduse employment. Also
amending the major street plan to remove
the extension of Allison Road and the
extension of Fox Farm Road due the
request meeting the review criteria.
>> Thank you. Do I have a second?
>> Second.
>> Okay, it's been moved and seconded by
com Commissioner Leard. Any discussion,
debate,
amendments?
>> Mr. Sure.
>> Um I I believe uh Commissioner Connor uh
first.
>> Mr. Chair, I just wanted to share that I
don't think my concerns about the
community college and the broader effect
on the students and and livestock there
have fully been addressed and I um don't
see this as beneficial for that
community and of course our community
college serves the broader community as
a whole.
>> Thank you, Commissioner Leair. Mr.
Chair, I I really had mixed feelings
about this when I I came in after
preparing for the meeting. I I think I
was going to be against
changing this land. U but I think I've
changed my mind and I'm going to support
it largely because of the land owners
um frustration or or
inability over the years to sell it. I I
would like to see it I would like to see
it developed like the master plan shows
like the land use plan uh as
particularly with the residential
because it seems like a prime lot to
build residential unlike for example the
first or the the stuff along Southwest
Drive that we heard about did not sound
like a very appropriate place for
residential development. Nor did nor do
I think is the 3200 acres up on top of
that bluff. Um, but I think Cheyenne I I
I hate to see the all the usable land in
the city get gobbled up by commercial
industrial uses and then there be a
real shortage of residential
um housing areas after that. So, I kind
of wanted to preserve this one because
it seemed like a fairly viable location.
But, I don't know. I I mean, I tell
myself maybe eventually
if the supply of residential areas
becomes constrained enough, somebody
will do what they have to do to to
develop it here. But I think for now,
I'm going to vote in favor of of uh this
or this motion.
>> Any other comments from discussion from
the commission?
And to address your concerns,
Commissioner Leair, I I came in with the
same general attitude. My concern is is
that by the time things are constrained
enough
to to make make the engineering
feasible,
we'll be running out of options. And
and I don't know if I'm going to have a
vote in this, but but
This I agree this is the hardest of the
lot because it is more closely
interwoven with the rest of the
residential fabric of the of our city
and
and Commissioner Connor has valid
concerns and one of my concerns all
along has been the lack of housing
surrounding the
community college. So with that,
will staff please call roll and and for
the public, as a reminder, this requires
an affirmative vote of at least four
members of the commission in order to
be recommended positively to the
governing body.
Bob Mia.
>> Hi.
>> Amy Hernandez.
>> No.
Tony Lair.
>> Hi.
>> Megan Connor.
>> No.
>> William Wigum.
>> Again,
>> no.
>> Mr. Chair, due to state statute and a
lack of having four affirmative votes,
the recommendation to the governing body
will be for denial.
>> And we'll stand. Well, I'm looking for a
motion on item L. I think staff is going
to remind us that that the future land
use map was not amended.
I move to recommend the governing body
deny the resoning of lots one and two
block one read land addition to BP
Business Park as shown in the attached
zone change map, noting that the project
does not meet the review criteria 1, 2,
5, and 8. the BP zoning request being
incompatible with the future land use
designations of urban residential,
mixeduse residential, and mixeduse
commercial.
Okay, it's been moved. Do I have a
second?
>> Second.
>> Okay.
Any discussion by the commission?
>> I struggle with the BP here. I've heard
all night that it's for the outskirts
and outside of Cheyenne. And this um
growing up on the southside, this does
not this is not outside of Cheyenne for
me. This is close to home.
Any further discussion?
Hearing none, will staff please call
roll. Mike and Connor,
>> yes.
>> Amy Hernandez,
>> hi.
>> Tony Lair,
>> hi. Bob Mio.
>> No.
>> Mr. Chair, that motion passes.
>> Okay. Thank you.
Other business or announcements,
>> Mr. Chair. Um I
I'm going to confidently say we will not
have a mid-month planning commission.
>> Um
and I should note hopefully hopefully as
of right now, we will only have two
items for July. So, it will not be 12
items again. It just be two.
>> Mr. Chair, if we're facing an agenda
like tonight, is there any way we can
try and break those up? Um, you know,
it's 11:00. I still have a baby I have
to go home to. It was not happy. So,
it's just um a big block of time for me
to give up late into the night. It's
tough. And I know other families
>> who want to come participate are
experiencing that, too. So, Mr. Chair,
unfortunately, when we have applications
that are submitted by applicants, those
are on specific timelines, we have to
move those forward on their timelines.
So, it just happened to this case where
we had this many submitted all at once
and they ended up on this timeline. Um,
it would staff would not be able to
break it up. it would have to follow the
timelines that we've already put out
there for the public when they look at
their schedules and when to submit their
applications.
>> Mr. Chair, members of the commission, I
just want to note that um as we move
forward with our one of our goals is to
do amendments to the bylaws. We can
explore a consent agenda option where
items that are routine could be added to
a consent agenda. But I just wanted to
remind you all that this is this seems
to be the story of our lives recently.
um as all of our council meetings have
been lasting long and there are still
two daytime and two evening meetings and
uh another public hear on anything with
annexation that will continue over the
next six weeks regarding this item these
items all these items. Um I did want to
note one thing real quick regarding um
updates. Uh we did have eight qualified
uh firms uh respond to our RFP for plan
Cheyenne. We are assembling a
selectioning committee which first phase
would be reading um up to eight
proposals that have 20 pages of
technical wording in there at size 11
font and that we'd ask for those to be
read
between whatever day a planning
commissioner would volunteer to be on
this committee and 10:00 a.m. on Monday
of next week. Um so we can narrow it
down to four and then one to two weeks
after that we would have an in-person uh
interview and a section committee. So,
if any of you all wish to uh read
through these eight uh qualified RFPs,
these proposals that we've had, um
please reach out to Seth Connor or I and
we will be sure to put you on the list.
And if we get multiple people that do
volunteer for this once in a planner's
opportunity, I would say um we will let
you know if there's competing interest
and we will figure out the best way to
roambo to be the victor.
So anyway, that's the only update I
have. So, please email uh one of the
three of us if you would be interested
in reviewing these.
Uh oh.
Are either of the two items on the July
agenda current items data centers?
>> Mr. chair. Uh
>> for BP zones
>> that I'm aware of,
they're not data centers. One is a BP
zone. It's an assigned zoning because it
is adjacent to North Range Business Park
and is actually becoming part of
Microsoft already has a county approved
site plan for basically their parking
and kind of lay down area for the
construction of the data center. But
they got a county approval for the site
plan and they need water. So they're
annexing it and most likely staff will
recommend the BP zone because it is
adjacent to North Range. It is already
industrial use. It isn't specifically
being bu built with a data center. So
otherwise the other item, no, you're
free.
Um, otherwise the other item that we
currently have is for a plat and the
plat has nothing to do with the data
center. I promise it's in Sweetgrass has
to do with the park. So,
anything else? With that, we're
adjourned.